<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The art of physick made plain &amp; easie by the learned D. Fambresarius ... ; translated out of his famous book De schola medecin by J.P.</title>
            <title>Scholae medicae. English</title>
            <author>La Framboisière, Nicholas Abraham de, b. 16th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48261</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15277401</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15277401</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103365</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48261)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103365)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1190:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The art of physick made plain &amp; easie by the learned D. Fambresarius ... ; translated out of his famous book De schola medecin by J.P.</title>
                  <title>Scholae medicae. English</title>
                  <author>La Framboisière, Nicholas Abraham de, b. 16th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 137, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H.C. for Dorman Newman ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of the author's Scholae medicae.</note>
                  <note>"Published for the publick benefit."</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [1] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Medicine --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103365:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103365:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ART OF PHYSICK MADE <hi>PLAIN</hi> &amp; <hi>EASIE;</hi> By the Learned D. <hi>FAMBRESARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> Phyſician to the moſt Chriſtian King, <hi>LEWIS</hi> XIV.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of his Famous Book, <hi>De Schola Medecin.</hi> By <hi>J. P.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for Publick Benefit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>H. C.</hi> for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey,</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:103365:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103365:2"/>
            <head>To <hi>J. Heroard,</hi> Lord of <hi>Valgrimos,</hi> Counſellor in the King's Sacred Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and one of the Chief Phyſicians.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Thought it proper, moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sir, to ſpeak ſomething by way of Preface concerning the Method of the Phyſical Schools Dedicated to the King. Before I ſent my Son <hi>Francis Fambreſarius</hi> to the Colledge of <hi>Montpellier,</hi> where he took his Degree of <hi>Doctor,</hi> I was willing to underſtand how much he had profited in the ſtudy of <hi>Phyſic,</hi> by the Inſtructions of his Father, and the Profeſſors of the <hi>Pariſian Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy,</hi> where he had been for four
<pb facs="tcp:103365:3"/>Years: Therefore I made uſe of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Queſtions and Exerciſes to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine him; which now, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of all Students, aſpiring to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in Phyſic, I thought good to make publick: For what is beneficial, by ſo much the more common it is, ſo much it is the better. I have us'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a Method no leſs plain then compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, in all the Queſtions touching the ſingular Parts of <hi>Phyſic.</hi> The general Parts of <hi>Phyſic</hi> are generally firſt examin'd, afterwards thoſe which are ſpecial, ſpecially; the Form of Examination accustom'd in the most Famous Academies, being exactly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. But why I have given to theſe <hi>Phyſical Queſtions</hi> the Title of <hi>Schools,</hi> there are two Reaſons: The one, becauſe that according to the beſt Regulated Academies, I have induc'd ſo many <hi>Doctors</hi> upon the Examination of a <hi>Candidate</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the whole <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>Phyſic</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:103365:3"/>did into ſo many Parts, the Senior <hi>Doctor</hi> beginning with the firſt, and ſo the reſt in their Order: Secondly, Becauſe that <hi>Cicero</hi> frequently uſes the Word <hi>Schools,</hi> for the Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions themſelves frequently us'd in the <hi>Schools;</hi> as in the firſt Book of his <hi>Tuſculan Queſtions.</hi> This I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways adjudg'd to be the moſt perfect Philoſophy, to be able to Diſpute co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piouſly and elegantly of the greateſt Queſtions; to which purpoſe I made it my Buſineſs that we might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to have <hi>Schools,</hi> after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the <hi>Greeks.</hi> As after thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, having ſeveral Friends with me in <hi>Tuſculanum,</hi> I endeavour'd to try what might be done in that kind; for as before I declaim'd and pleaded Cauſes, which no man did longer then my ſelf; ſo now I make uſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of Declaiming in my <hi>Old Age.</hi> I bid them put the Queſtion which any one deſires to be reſolv'd
<pb facs="tcp:103365:4"/>in, and then either ſitting or walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I diſpute it. Therefore have I divided the <hi>Schools</hi> or <hi>Exerciſes</hi> of five days into ſo many Books. But I ſhall detain thee no longer in the Porch, <hi>(Moſt Noble Hero of our Art)</hi> I only beg of thee, to accept of theſe my Lucubrations with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Aſpect; which will add to the Heap of your former Kindneſſes to me. Live long, for our Kings, for thy own, and our ſake, <hi>Fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Paris, <date>In the Calends of <hi>March,</hi> 1622.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:103365:4"/>
            <head>THE DEFINITION OF <hi>Phyſick: <hi>The Diviſion of it; the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Practice of which, is the Buſineſs of a</hi>
               </hi> Phyſician.</head>
            <div n="1" type="disputation">
               <head>Dean of the Colledge.</head>
               <p>IT was a great Saying of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Philoſopher, or rather O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator <hi>Tully,</hi> That a Diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any Subject undertaken, by Reaſon ought to begin from the Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the thing about which the Diſpute ariſes, may be underſtood:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103365:5"/>Therefore, ſince we are going to diſpute concerning Phyſic, my firſt <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, What is <hi>Phyſic?</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Candidate.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt reverend Dean, <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic,</hi> by <hi>Galen,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Art,</hi> is defin'd to be the <hi>Art of Preſerving</hi> preſent, and the <hi>Reſtorer</hi> of decay'd Health. And in his <hi>Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Book,</hi> A Knowledge protecting <hi>Health,</hi> and expelling <hi>Diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>Hippocrates</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Wind,</hi> from the Effects, it is defin'd to be an Addition of what is defective, and a detracting of what is ſuperfluous.</p>
                  <p>By <hi>Herophilus,</hi> from the Subject, The Knowledge of what is wholſom, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wholſom, or between both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>Neither of theſe Definitions pleaſe me; That of <hi>Galen,</hi> becauſe Phyſic is neither an Art nor a Science. That it is no Art, I thus demonſtrate.</p>
                  <p>An Art is a Syſteme of Homogeneous Precepts methodically diſpos'd, for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the End. But the Precepts of Phyſic are not Homogeneous, but He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous: Therefore Phyſic is no Art.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny your <hi>Minor,</hi> moſt learned Maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103365:5"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove it thus; Phyſic treats of things wholeſom and unwholeſom; but wholeſom and unwholeſom are He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous; therefore the Precepts of Phyſic are Heterogeneous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I anſwer, That tho in regard of the Variety of the Subject Matter, they may ſeem to be Heterogeneous, yet in regard of their Uniformity they are <hi>Homogeneous.</hi> Moreover, all Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Theſes's tho they may be diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and oppoſitely divided one from the other, yet in regard they all conſpire to the ſame end, therefore they may be ſaid to be Homogeneous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>But I deny Phyſic to be a Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
                  <p>For a Science is only of things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and perpetual.</p>
                  <p>But Phyſic teaches contingent Matters and Things that may be otherwiſe then at preſent they are.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Phyſic is no Science.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny your <hi>Minor.</hi> For tho Phyſic may have a contingent End, yet it conſiſts of Axioms both neceſſary and perpetual.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:103365:6"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>There are many things in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic which are controverted, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed through variety of diſſenting Opinions, which are oppoſite to Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: and therefore the Theoremes or Rules of Phyſic are not always perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally certain nor neceſſary.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the Conſequence. For tho ſome Probable Problemes may be controverted in Phyſic, however the Univerſal Theoremes eſtabliſhed by a Demonſtration are certain and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, and conſequently may be ſaid to be compos'd of a Science.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>But Phyſic treats of a vaſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Particulars and Singulars ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Senſes, of which no knowledge may be had, as being a habit of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, acquir'd by Demonſtration. Therefore Phyſic is no Knowledge.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the Antecedent: For Phyſic does not diſcourſe of <hi>Peter</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> in particular, but of a ſound or ſick body in general, and that according to the methods of Knowledge; tho in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a Phyſician in particular conſiders all thoſe things that are ſubject to the Senſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103365:6"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you ſay to this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Candidate?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The End of a Science is only Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation.</p>
                  <p>But the End of Phyſic is an Action, the obtaining of Health.</p>
                  <p>Therefore Phyſic is not a Science.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I diſtinguiſh the <hi>Major.</hi> The End indeed of ſpeculative Knowledge is only Contemplation: But the End of Practical Science is Action. Add to this, that Phyſic is twofold, Teaching, and Practiſing. The End of Inſtructing Phyſic is the true and certain know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſical Precepts: But the End of Practical Phyſic is Action; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and Reſtoration of Health.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>The Definition which <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> give of Phyſic, I thus oppoſe:</p>
                  <p>Every true Definition conſiſts of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> or Kind, and Difference; but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Addition nor Detraction are Kinds of Phyſic.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the <hi>Major.</hi> For neither of thoſe Actions ſeparately, but both together are the <hi>Genus</hi> of Phyſic.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> The <hi>Genus</hi> of Phyſick is <hi>Faculty:</hi> Therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103365:7"/>of thoſe Actions can be ſaid to be the <hi>Genus</hi> of Phyſic.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the Conſequence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove it thus: The <hi>Genus</hi> contains the ſeveral Cauſes that equally belong to the ſeveral <hi>Species:</hi> Thus <hi>Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Creature,</hi> the <hi>Genus</hi> of Man and Beaſt, contains Corporeal Subſtance, which is the Matter, and the Faculty of Life and Sence, which is the Common Form of Man and Beaſt.</p>
                  <p>But Addition and Detraction are the Effects of Phyſic: For Phyſic adds what is wanting, and detracts what is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, and all this for the reſtoration of Health: And therefore neither can be ſaid to be the <hi>Genus</hi> of Phyſic.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I Anſwer, That <hi>Hippocrates</hi>'s Definition of Phyſic is not Eſſential, but from the Effects. Where the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are Metonymically taken for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty from whence they proceed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Then for the Definition of <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> I thus refute it. There is no ſuch thing as a Neuter Body: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Phyſic is by him ill defin'd to be a Science of things wholeſom, unwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, or neither.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103365:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the Antecedent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove it thus: A ſound Body is that which enjoys Health; an unſound Body, that which labours under a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
                  <p>But the Body is either perpetually un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound or in Health:</p>
                  <p>Therefore no Neuter Body.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I deny the <hi>Minor,</hi> For that is ſaid to be a neuter Conſtitution, when the Body is ſaid to be neither ſick nor well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> Sound and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthy are immediate Contraries, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle:</hi> Therefore ſeeing Health and Sickneſs are diametrically oppoſite, there can be no middle Conſtitution between 'em.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I Anſwer, Health and Sickneſs are immediately oppoſite according to <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but not according to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Galen</hi> teaches the contrary, where he ſays, That Health is Symmetry, Sickneſs Diſorder: But there is no Medium between Symmetry and Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103365:8"/>
                  <p>Beſides, Health is an Affection that produces a good, and not a ſenſibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd Action. But Sickneſs produces an Action ſenſibly deprav'd: now then between that which is ſenſibly and not ſenſibly deprav'd, there is no <hi>Medium.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I declare alſo this farther upon the Authority of <hi>Galen;</hi> When a Body ceaſes to be healthful, it becomes ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: And in another place; When the Body paſſes from Health into Sickneſs, the Tranſition is imperceptible. And in another place; He that can act and do as he was wont to do, according to all the Operations of the Body, is in Health; he that cannot, is unſound and Sick. And the Latitude of Health extends it ſelf from the moſt perfect o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. to a ſenſible failing in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration: the Diſeaſe beginning from that ſenſible Depravation. Now nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in theſe, nor many other paeces, do's <hi>Galen</hi> make any mention of the <hi>Medium;</hi> tho ſometimes he puts a Neuter between Sound and Sick.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>I Anſwer, <hi>Galen</hi> ſometimes takes Health in a larger ſence, ſometimes he contracts it within a narrower Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103365:8"/>Affirming, that there is a certain ſence in Habit, which is firm and ſtable, another in the Diſpoſition and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is not ſo durable, but rather ſo infirm, as to be ſubject to every ſlight Injury. Seeing therefore <hi>Galen</hi> accompts him ſound, in whom the wonted Offices of the parts do not ceaſe their proper Exerciſes, tho they operate but feebly; then certainly thoſe <hi>Neuters</hi> in decay, that are falling into Sickneſs, and thoſe <hi>Neuters</hi> in Health, who are upon reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very; he alſo reck'ns among the Sound, and takes in the ſtate of Neutrality with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Limits of Health. But when he excludes both Conditions as unſound, and not ſufficient to act according as Nature requires, there he grants a Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Condition, which is not ſound, in regard that preſervation is not proper for it; but is requiſite for Neuters fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into a Diſtemper, by way of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, and to thoſe that are newly recovered from a Diſtemper by way of Reſtoration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>How many are the Parts of <hi>Phyſic.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103365:9"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>Four. That which contains the Speculation of Nature, called <hi>Phyſiology;</hi> that which comprehends the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Health; that which treats of the Symptoms and Affections, call'd <hi>Pathology;</hi> and the laſt which treats of Med'cines and Remedies in particular: Some there are who reckon five, making the Conſideration of Cauſes and Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms to be two parts, tho indeed they are both comprehended under <hi>Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>This Diviſion of <hi>Phyſic</hi> does not pleaſe me. For Natural Phyloſophy is a ſpeculative Science; Phyſic an active Art; ſo that <hi>Phyſiology</hi> cannot be a part of both; but <hi>Phyſiology</hi> is a part of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Philoſophy,</hi> and therefore no part of <hi>Phyſic.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus far you argue diſcreetly, Maſter; <hi>Phyſiology</hi> is a part of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> therefore no part of <hi>Phyſic.</hi> But I deny <hi>Phyſiology</hi> to be a part of <hi>Natural Philoſophy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>I prove it thus; Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, as of all other Animals, ſo it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly deſcribes the Body of Man. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Phyſiology</hi> is a part of Natural Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:103365:9"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Philoſophy indeed conſiders the Body of Man as it is natural in general; but <hi>Phyſiology</hi> which is accompted the firſt part of <hi>Phyſic,</hi> conſiders the Body particularly, whether ſound, or diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd, or between both. So that <hi>Phyſic</hi> is by ſome ſaid to be particular to man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dean.</speaker>
                  <p>How many things are perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requiſite for the obtaining the perfect knowledge of <hi>Phyſic?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>Three; Things natural, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Phyſiology</hi> employs it ſelf: Things not natural, which the contemplation of Health appropriates to it ſelf, in the knowledge of which <hi>Pathology,</hi> in the expulſion and reſiſtance of which, the <hi>Ther apeutic</hi> parts buſie themſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Which d'ye call things Natural?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe things which conſtitute the Nature of Man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How many ſorts of things Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral may be reck'n'd up?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Seven in all. The Elements; the Temperaments, the Parts, the Humors, the Spirits, the Faculties and Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Of the Elements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>What is an Element?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>An Element is the ſmalleſt part of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103365:10"/>that, of which it is an Element, <hi>Gal.</hi> l. 1. <hi>of Elements.</hi> Now he calls the ſmalleſt part the moſt ſimple; which cannot be divided into other parts different in <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> An Element is therefore the moſt ſimple part of a mixt Body.</p>
                  <p>By others an Element is divided into a ſimple Body, of which any thing is firſt made, and into which at laſt it is again diſſolv'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>By this reaſon the Bones, Muſcles, Fleſh, and other Similar parts ſhall be ſaid to be the Elements of Humane Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, becauſe they are ſimple Bodies of the Organic Members, are firſt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and into which they are every one divided.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo: For though they appear Simple to the Senſes, yet are they really compos'd of the four Elements, and diſſolv'd at length into them again; in regard the laſt diſſolution of mixt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſtops in the Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How! Are not the Elements them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, the common beginnings of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Body's, diſſolv'd into Matter and Form?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:103365:10"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>In thought it ſeems to be ſo, but not in reality. For the Elements are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be divided by Reaſon, and not by actual Operation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>What Difference is there between Principles and Elements?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>The Difference is twofold: Firſt, The Elements proceed out of others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and out of one another. But Principles proceed neither from others, nor from themſelves, but out of themſelves produce all Natural things.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, The Elements are of the ſame <hi>Genus</hi> with thoſe things of which they are Elements: But Principles can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be of the ſame <hi>Genus</hi> with thoſe things of which they are Principles; Wherefore in regard that Elements are Bodies, it is apparent, that thoſe things of which they are Elements are Bodies; but the Principles of Bodies are Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How many Elements are there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Four: Fire, Air, Water and Earth, which frequently by <hi>Hippocrates</hi> are call'd Hot, Moiſt, Cold and Dry.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103365:11"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>By what Arguments are the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments prov'd to be four?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Chiefly by three. Firſt, becauſe they are the firſt four Elements liable to the ſenſe of Feeling, and ſo many real Agreements of Tangible Qualities. Next, becauſe the four Elements concur to the forming of mix'd Bodies. Laſtly, Becauſe all mixt Bodies are diſſolv'd back into the four Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>I would have thee demonſtrate how Human Bodies are compos'd of theſe four Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>It is the general Aſſent of all that our Bodies are compos'd of Organic Members in the firſt place; then thoſe Organic Members are perfected out of a Compoſure of ſimilar parts, which ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar parts deduce their Original from the Seed and Maternal Bloud, both proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a mixture of Humors; which mixture ariſes from the Meat and Drink put into the Body; the product of which, whether the Fleſh of Land-Creatures, or of Fiſh, whether Fruit-Trees, or Herbs and Flowers, is only the promiſcuous concourſe and mixture of the Elements. Seeing then our Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103365:11"/>proceeds from the Elements, from our Nouriſhment the Humors, from the Humors the Similar Parts, from the Similar Parts the Organic Members; from the Organic parts of Human Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, it is manifeſt that the ſame is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd according to the method of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, out of the four Elements: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over that Human Bodies conſiſt of thoſe firſt Elements, is plain from their laſt Diſſolution; for that when a man dies, all things return from whence they came. Thus the innate heat diſſipates and flies away to the Element of Fire. His Breath returns partly to the Fire, partly to the Air. The flowing Humor becomes Water again. The more ſolid, thick and firm parts, when once the Moiſture is exhauſted, dry up and moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to duſt. This the moſt admired <hi>Hippocrates</hi> firſt gave us to underſtand, where he declares, that when Man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, every thing ſeparates to its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Nature, and returns to thoſe Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of which it was at firſt compos'd. The Moiſt to the Moiſt; the Dry to the Dry; the Hot to the Hot; and Cold to the Cold.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:103365:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell us more plainly how human Body is generated out of the four Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>The Body of Man is not compos'd of the Bodies of the Elements alone, but of their conjoyn'd Qualities, nor theſe neither pure, but intermixt and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd, according as they act of ſuffer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Repeat the Qualities of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Elements.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Fire is hot in the Extream, remiſly dry. Air moiſt in Extremity, remiſly hot. Earth cold in the Extream, remiſly moiſt. The Earth dry in the Extream, remiſly cold. So that the firſt four Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities are Heat, Cold, Moyſture and Drought: Of which the Elements are the firſt Subjects; and out of their Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Temperament our Bodies are compos'd; which while the Mixture and Temperament remain equal and juſt, are in perfect Health; but when that Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Temperament fails, or is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd by ſome Accident, the Body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes diſtemper'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>What is Mixture?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Mixture is the Union of Alter'd things apt to be mixt.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:103365:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How is Mixture made, either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Qualities or the Forms, or in the whole?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Qualities are alter'd, Forms uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the whole Elements mixt with the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Shew me more diſtinctly the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Mixture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Alteration precedes Mixture, or rather the Conflict of contrary Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties precede the acting and ſuffering of the Touch; for all Phyſical Agents act by the Touch. And therefore all Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that concur to conſtitute a mixt Body, touch one another in the firſt place; then act one upon another by their Repugnancy and Contrariety, and ſo by their mutual acting and ſuffering, divide themſelves into the ſmalleſt parts imaginable, make way and enter every where, and this is call'd Mixture in the whole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Then you ſay, Subſtances are mixt with Subſtances.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe no Mixture is made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repugnancy; but Subſtance is not repugnant to Subſtance.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:103365:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Subſtance is not repugnant to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it ſelf, as it is Subſtance; but in reſpect of its Qualities. So Fire in its whole Form and Subſtance does not reſiſt Fire; but one in its Quality; Fire being hot, and Water cold. Alteration is not a mutation or change of Forms, but Qualities. The Elements through their mutual Conteſts are alter'd in their Conteſts, are alter'd in their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and are temper'd by their being broken and pierc'd; taking away the Repugnancy, they are eaſily united. But from the Union of the Forms of every Element, one Form of a mixt Body ariſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Temperaments.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Temperament?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Temperament is a proportion of the four chief Elementary Qualities proper for the true exerciſe of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Functions. <hi>Avicen</hi> defines a Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament to be a Quality ariſing from the Elements proportionably mixt. <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> calls it the Beginning of Natural Functions and Faculties. <hi>Averrhoes,</hi> the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103365:13"/>Form of a mixt Body. But this laſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition does not pleaſe me, becauſe the form of a mixt Body is a Subſtance, but Temperament is an Accident in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Qualities.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Think you a Mixture of the firſt Qualities may be made without a Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Elements?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By no means. For tho in this, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament differs from Mixture, that the latter is made proper to the Elements, the former to the Qualities, yet are they ſo conjoyn'd, that neither Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can be made without the aid of Efficient Qualities, nor Temperament without the ſubſtance of all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. So that Temperament is a kind of Harmony of the four principal Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, proceeding from the Mixture of all the Elements.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the Differences of Temperaments in general?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Nine. One Temperate, eight without Temperature; of which four are ſimple; Hot, Cold, Moiſt, Dry, and as many compounded; as Hot and Moiſt, Hot and Dry; Cold and Moiſt, and Cold and Dry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103365:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is that which is ſaid to be Temperate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which the <hi>Greeks</hi> call well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper'd, which is as it were the Rule and Meaſure of all Temperaments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many kinds is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold. The one Temper'd ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and to weight; the other to Juſtice in ſeveral <hi>Genus</hi>'s.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What call ye Temperament abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and to weight?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That in which there is an even and equal Portion of Elements mixt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; no more of hot then moiſt, no more of cold then dry.</p>
                     <p>This <hi>Galen</hi> believes to be rather ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary, then real; or if at any time it happen to be, yet that it laſts but a very ſhort time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What call ye Temper'd to Juſtice in ſeveral kinds?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which does not contain an exact evenneſs of Contraries, but ſuch a decent Mediocrity as its Nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, and beſt agrees with the <hi>Genus</hi> or <hi>Species:</hi> So that the equality of the Mixture is not to be meaſur'd by Arith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metical, but Geometrical Proportion.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103365:14"/>For Juſtice gives to every thing its due, according to Dignity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the ſimple Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments without Temper?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such Temperatures wherein one of the four Qualities exceeds, as either Heat, Cold, Moiſture, or Drought.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Compounded?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>In which there is an Exceſs of two Qualities: as a Temperature hot and moiſt, in which the Heat exceeds the Cold, and Moiſture Drineſs. Cold and dry, which has more of Cold then Heat, and more of dry then moiſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt in vain diſtinguiſh'd the Temperaments into Simple and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound; when there is no ſimple Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raments, but all are compounded.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That I deny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove it thus: A Simple Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament is that wherein one only Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment prevails; as Hot, in whoſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament Fire prevails; Cold, in which Fire overcomes.</p>
                     <p>But every Element has two Qualities; for Fire is hot and dry, Water cold and moiſt.</p>
                     <p>Therefore there is no ſimple Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:103365:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That is call'd a Simple Tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein one Quality prevails, not one Element.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Againſt thy Anſwer I thus ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue:</p>
                     <p>Seeing that Quality is an Accident, it cannot ſubſiſt by it ſelf without a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: And therefore if any Quality of an Eſement prove ſuperior, of neceſſity he Element to which it belongs muſt tprevail.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Altho every Element have two Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, there is but one which is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, from which the Temperament de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives its name: But therefore is it call'd a Temperament hot or cold, becauſe the Heat prevails over the contrary Cold, or the Cold over the contrary Heat, with an equality of moiſt and dry: And it it call'd a moiſt and dry Temper; becauſe the moiſt is more powerful then the dry, or the dry then the moiſt, with an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of hot and cold.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:103365:15"/>
                  <head>Of the Parts.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus much for the Elements and Temperaments; now let us come to the Parts. What is a Part?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word <hi>Part,</hi> in a large ſenſe, ſignifies whatever makes up the whole frame of Human Body; for whatever compleats and perfects the whole, is call'd a Part, as <hi>Galen</hi> teſtifies. In this large and extended ſignification <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> uſes the Word, when he calls the Humors and Spirits Parts. But by <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> a <hi>Part</hi> is properly deſcribed to be a Body cohering to the whole, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd by Life, common to both, and provided for ſuch a Uſe or Function: By which Definition Humors and Spirits are excluded out of the number of Parts, becauſe they never ſtay or cohere, but are carry'd with a ſwift motion through the Veins and Arteries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Diviſion of Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diviſion of Parts is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; but the chief Diviſion is into ſuch as contain, and ſuch as are contained.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the containing parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:103365:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſolid parts which are upheld by themſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are they divided?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Into Similar and Diſſimilar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are Similar Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Similar Parts, ſo call'd, as being of the ſame Nature, are ſuch as conſiſt of one equal Subſtance, every way like to its ſelf, in which as being ſmalleſt to the Sence, the Diſſolution of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy conſiſts; for which reaſon they are ſometimes call'd Simple and Primary; and ſometimes ſenſible Elements, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing moſt ſimple to the Senſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are Similar Parts divided?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Into Spermatic and Sanguine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Spermatick Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as conſiſt of Seed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the Similar Sper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matic Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Nine. Bones, Muſcles, Ligaments, Fibres, Membranes, Nerves, Veins, Arteries and Skin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But I ſay, Nerves, Veins, Arte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Skin are Diſſimilar Parts; for <hi>Galen, Hippoc.</hi> and <hi>Plat.</hi> Of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Parts,</hi> aſſert, that the Nerves are Marrowy within, Membrany without;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103365:16"/>that the body of the Veins and Nerves are interwoven with Membranes, and ſeveral <hi>Fibres;</hi> and that the Skin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of Nerves, Veins and Arteries; and therefore they ought not to be numbred among the ſimilar Parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, There are two ſorts of Similar Parts; for ſome are really Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as Bones, Muſcles, Ligaments, Fibres, Membranes; other only in the judgment of Sence; and ſo Nerves, Veins, Arteries and Skin ſhall be Similar Parts, becauſe upon the firſt view their ſubſtance ſeems to be of the ſame kind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Sanguinary Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Which have their Original from the Blood, as Fleſh and Fat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Diſſimilar Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diſſimilar Parts are ſuch as are not compos'd of parts of the ſame Nature, but of ſeveral differing in <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</hi> They are otherwiſe call'd Orga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic, as being the Inſtruments of which the Faculties and Functions of the Mind make uſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are the Organic Parts divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Into Animal, Vital and Natural;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103365:17"/>and every one of theſe, into Principal and Aſſiſtant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'you call the Animal, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, and Natural Parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Inſtruments of the Animal, Vital and Natural Functions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye call the Principal part?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That part which governs the reſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Aſſiſting parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe which are ſubſervient to the Principal, and derive their Original from it for the moſt part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the principal Organ of the Animal Function?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Brain; for it is the common Original of all the Animal Functions, as well ſenſitive, as moving; the Seat of the Animal Spirit, and the beginning of the Nerves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the Organs aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Brain in the exerciſe of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Function?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold; for ſome conveigh the Animal Faculty to ſenſe and motion, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers operate; of which ſort are all the proper Organs of every Senſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior and voluntary motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:103365:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Organs that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh the Faculty of ſenſe and motion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſenſitive and moving Nerves?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the proper Organs of every Senſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Eyes, of ſeeing; the Ears, of hearing; the Noſe, of ſmelling; the Tongue, of taſte; and the Skin, of feeling.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>which are the proper Organs of voluntary motion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Muſcles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the principal Organ of the Vital Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Heart; for it is the fountain of Vital Faculty and Spirit; the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Seat of native Heat, and the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of the Arteries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Organs ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the Heart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are twofold; the Organs of Reſpiration, and of the Pulſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Organs of Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are of three ſorts; ſome for conveighance, others for reception, others for motion.</p>
                     <p>The Organs that conveigh the Air,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103365:18"/>the Wind-pipe and rough Artery: The Lungs receive the Air down in, and prepare it for the Heart: The moving Organs are ſixty five Muſcles, dilating and contracting the Breaſt; for the Air is not drawn, nor the Vapors ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, without the motion of the Breaſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Inſtruments for the Pulſes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Arteries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the principal Organ of the Natural Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Liver; for it is the Original of the natural Faculty, and of all the Veins, and the firſt Inſtrument of the generation of Blood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Organs are ſubſervient to the natural Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two ſorts; for ſome are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated for nouriſhment, others ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for generation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the aſſiſting Organs of nouriſhment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are of three ſorts; ſome for preparation, ſome for purgation, and ſome for diſtribution of the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:103365:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are for preparation of the Nouriſhment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Mouth and Stomach prepare the Nouriſhment, the one by Maſtica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the other by Concoction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which ſerve for Purgation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are of two ſorts: for it is the Office of ſome to purge the <hi>Chylus;</hi> for the Excrements of the <hi>Chylus</hi> are ſent forth from the Belly; but the Blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Gall, the Spleen, the Kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys and Bladder are the Organs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to purge the Bloud; for they receive and ſeparate from the Bloud thoſe excrementitious Humors begot in the Chylous matter at the time that it turns to Bloud.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which ſerve for the Diſtribution of the Nouriſhment?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Veins,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt reck'nd up all the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans ſerving to Nouriſhment, now give me an accompt of the Organs of Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Organs of Generation, ſome are common both to Male and Female, ſome proper to each Sex.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>which are common to both Sexes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103365:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Teſticles and Spermatick Veſſels, as well preparing, as conveighing the Seed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which Proper?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Yard to the Male, the Womb to the Female.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Humors.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Having thus reck'nd up the parts containing, now for the parts contain'd. Which then are the Parts contain'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The fluid parts, which are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the help of others, ſuch as are the Humors and Spirits.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many Humors are contain'd in the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides the Primogeneous Humor, or that which comes naturally of it ſelf, there are two other adventitious, that is to ſay, the Alimentary and Excremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye mean by the Primoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Humor?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A certain Oily ſubſtance, bred in the more ſolid parts of the Body, from their firſt Original, being the Baſis and Seat of Spirit and innate Heat, and is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103365:19"/>therefore call'd by the name of Radical Moiſture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which d'ye call the Alimentary humors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Juices of the ſolid parts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for nouriſhment, which derive their original from a commixture of the four Elements.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which the Excrementitious?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſuperfluous moiſture in the Body, uſeful to Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are the Alimentary humors diſtinguiſhed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Into Primary and Secondary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are accompted the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe which are diſtributed by the <hi>Chylus</hi> in the Liver, by the Power of its natural inbred heat, through the Veins to the ſeveral parts of the Body for their Nouriſhment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many Primary Humors are there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Four. Bloud, Choler, Melancholy, and Flegm. Which are all mix'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the Veins. This mixture of the four Humors is call'd the <hi>Sanguinary</hi> Maſs by reaſon that the Bloud has the greateſt ſhare in it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103365:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is to be underſtood by the Word <hi>Blood?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word Blood is ſometimes taken in a diffuſive Sence for the whole Maſs of the Bloud; but properly it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the more pure and enlivening part of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Temperature of the Bloud?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Bloud, generally taken for the whole Maſs of Bloud, is well tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per'd, in regard the temperature ariſes from an equal mixture of the future contrary humors; together with a juſt proportion and decent Harmony of the ſame: but being conſider'd in it ſelf, as pure and limpid, it is hot and moiſt, and ſomthing of the nature of Air: Nor is it differenc'd from the reſt of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors by reaſon of this peculiar temper only, but alſo by its Conſiſtency, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, Taſte and Uſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Conſiſtency of the Bloud, what its Colour, Taſte and Uſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Bloud is of a conſiſtency ſo thin, that while it is kept within the bounds of Nature, it appears neither
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:103365:20"/>thicker nor thinner, of a red Colour, and ſweet Taſte. It nouriſhes chiefly the muſculous parts, while it hai the predominancy; and makes men fleſhy, lively, handſom, good diſpoſition'd and cheerful.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>In what Ages is the Bloud moſt prevalent?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>In Children, Youth and Young men; thus <hi>Galen</hi> affirms, That Boys, Young men, and Striplings between both, enjoy moſt of the ſanguine Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, as in whom the firſt Principles of Life are yet moſt vigorous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When does it moſt abound in the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Bloud is moſt plentiful in the Spring, becauſe then the Froſts are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd, and the Waters are let looſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Opinion of <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is <hi>Choler?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Alimentary Choler is the more thin part of the Sanguinary Maſs, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the Nature of Fire, in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perament hot and dry, of a pale or yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Colour, bitter in Taſte; and cauſes men to be lean, tough, active, raſh and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103365:21"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:103365:21"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103365:22"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="31" facs="tcp:103365:22"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:103365:23"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="33" facs="tcp:103365:23"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="34" facs="tcp:103365:24"/>haſty, nouriſhing thoſe parts which are moſt akin to its Nature, wherein it differs from the excrementitious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the excrementitious Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is ſent to the Bladder or Bagg of the Gall, to haſten the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion of the Excrements, and to cleanſe the Guts of any ſlimy matter ſticking to them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>In what ſort of perſons is Choler moſt predominant?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Yellow Choler abounds moſt in thoſe who are in the Prime of their Age, as <hi>Galen</hi> avers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When does it moſt abound?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Choler abounds moſt in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> declares: as alſo in a dry ſeaſon of the Air, for that drought renders the hands more Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leric in quality, as <hi>Galen</hi> delivers his judgment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Melancholy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Alimentary Melancholy is the thicker part of the Sanguinary Maſs, of the nature of the Earth, in temper cold and dry, of a black colour, ſowr in taſte, and renders men ſad, thoughtful,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:103365:24"/>moroſe, ſevere and conſtant; it nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes the moſt ſolid and dry parts of the Body, as the Bones; where it dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from the excrementitious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the excrementitious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is carried to the Milt; where it is ſeparated from the more uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Juice that affords it nouriſhment, and ſo poured out into the Stomach, to excite the Appetite, and to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the Faculty which retains the meat there during Concoction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſort of People are moſt ſubject to Melancholy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Black Melancholy is moſt exuberant in the declining Age of Men, by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>Galen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When does it moſt abound in the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Black Melancholy abounds moſt in the Autumnal Seaſon, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> relates.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Flegm?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Alimentary Flegm is the more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid part of the ſanguinary Maſs, of the nature of Water, in temper cold and moiſt, of a white colour, and ſweet
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:103365:25"/>Taſte, or rather without any ſavour. It makes men ſloathful, ſleepy, dull, fat, white, and effeminate; it nouriſhes the Brain, and other cold and moiſt parts of the Body; wherein it chiefly differs from the Excrementitious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Excrementitious Flegm.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Serous</hi> or Whey-like ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluity which the Kidneys ſeparate from the Bloud, and conveigh to the Bladder through the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reters,</hi> where it is called Urine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>At what Age is Flegm moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dundant?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Flegm abounds moſt in old Age, by reaſon of the decay of the Natural Heat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When does it moſt abound in the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Winter fills the Body with Flegm, by reaſon of the great plenty of Rain, and the length of the Nights, as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> declares. A moiſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Air works alſo the ſame Effect; for the moiſture of the ambient Air increaſes flegmatic Humors, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a great many watery ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:103365:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are accounted the ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dary Humors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as derive their Original from the former in any part of the Body; where they are more exactly prepar'd by the laſt concoction: from whence two manifeſt Excrements proceed, Sweat and Ordure; beſides what goes forth by inſenſible Tranſpiration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the ſecondary Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are reck'nd to be in number four; according to the diverſity of thoſe Alterations which they undergo, while they are prepar'd for the nouriſhment of every part.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is that which is contain'd in the ſmall Veins, thence ready to empty it ſelf into the vacant ſpaces.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond, that which being diffus'd into the ſubſtance of the Part, penetrates it like a kind of Dew.</p>
                     <p>The third, that which gathering a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Hair, ſticks to it.</p>
                     <p>And the laſt is a thickn'd Liquor that ſticks in ſuch a manner to the Fibres, that it ſeems to be chang'd into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of a Similar Part. And thus the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:103365:26"/>Humors through the variety of their Alteration, at length change into the Nature of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Think'ſt thou the Humors conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting the Nature of the Body to be perpetually Natural?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo: for as when the Humors obſerve their Mixture and Temper, they are natural; ſo when they fall from their equal Conſtitution, they become devious, and wanderers from Nature. Whence it happens that Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are ſometimes ſound, ſometimes ſick; according to that of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> containing in it ſelf Bloud and Flegm, black and yellow Melancholy, by which the Nature of the Body is conſtituted, and by means of which it is either ſick or well; for by the benefit of theſe it is in health when they anſwer one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in reference to Temperament, in Quantity, and Quality; and in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Mixture, when they are mix'd, and not ſeparated one from the other.</p>
                     <p>But the Body is ſick through the ill operation of theſe; when in reference to Temperament, one abounds, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is defective in Quality; or when
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:103365:26"/>in Quality, when the faculty of the one is more intenſe, of the other more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs. Or elſe in reference to Mixture, when one Humour ſeparates from the reſt of the Maſs; for when one Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is ſeparated from the reſt of the Maſs, there muſt of neceſſity be ſome Diſtemper in that part, from whence the Humour is departed contrary to Nature; or in that part where it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flows contrary to Nature; which Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour departing from the reſt, if it be expell'd without the Body, begets a ſimple Diſeaſe; but if it remain within the Body, it will cauſe a double Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in that Part which it has left, through Evacuation, and in the Part where it abounds, by Repletion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How does the Blood deviate from the Rule of Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When it grows corrupt, that is, when the thinner portion of it turns to yellow, the thicker to black <hi>Choler;</hi> by which it becomes fuller of Choler and Melancholy: Or if it be vitiated by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Humors which flow into the Veins from the Bag of the Gall, or any other Parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:103365:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How does Choler deviate from Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When either within or without the Veins it changes its Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Choler are bred in the Veins contrary to Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three ſorts; the pale, the yolk-colour'd, and the black.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How does Choler become pale?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By the mixture of the ſerous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How of the colour of the Yolk of an Egg?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is compounded of yellow and pale, while the Acrimony of the Unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Heat is boyl'd up as it were to a Conſiſtency, ſo that of a thin, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a thick ſubſtance, and the colour of it is likewiſe heightn'd, reſembling the colour of a raw yolk of an Egg.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How does black Choler depart from its natural courſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Black Choler is made of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telline by the extremity of Heat and Burning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Choler are bred out of the Veins contrary to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:103365:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three ſorts; the Leek-colour'd, the Ruſt-colour'd, and the Woad-co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Matter which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are generated chiefly in the Stomach, of Meats that are of vicious and evil Juice; and the Vitelline Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler poured forth into the Stomach, is frequently chang'd into one or other of theſe, contracting a change of colour from the coldneſs of the Place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What cauſes the Effects of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy againſt Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the MeIancholic Humor, by extremity of Heat is as it were burnt to aſhes; ſo that it becomes ſharp and biting, differing from the Melancholic Juice, as burnt Lees from not burnt. This ſort of Melancholy is call'd Black Choler, and Black-choleric Humor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What cauſes in Flegm its contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Effects?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When it is corrupted either in the Veins, or without the Veins.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Flegm are bred in the Veins againſt Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:103365:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two ſorts; <hi>Acid</hi> and <hi>Salt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Acid;</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is chiefly raw and crude, which beſides the firſt and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Alteration in the Stomach has had no other Concoction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How comes Flegm to be ſalt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By the corruption of ſweet Flegm through the mixture of the ſerous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Flegm are bred without the Veins?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Four ſorts; the Watery, the Snotty, the Glaſſy, and the Pargetty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Watery?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is ſo thin that it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtils from the Noſtrils, or falls from the Brains upon the lower parts like Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Mucous?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which by the heat of the Parts is thicken'd into the ſubſtance of Snot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Vitrous or Glaſſy;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which in colour and ſubſtance is like melted Glaſs, thicker and colder then the Snotty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:103365:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What the <hi>Pargetty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which at length becomes as thick and hard as Parget; ſuch as is ſometimes ſeen in the Joynts, in which, after preceding thinner diſtillation, and diſſolutions of the thinner part of the Matter, at laſt appears a piece of Flegm hardn'd like a Pumice-Stone.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Spirits.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Leaving the <hi>Humors,</hi> let us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to the <hi>Spirits.</hi> Why are they call'd Impulſive by <hi>Hippocrates?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe that by their means the Corporeal Bulks of Living Creatures are mov'd, perceive, live and ſubſiſt; even by their aid the dull and heavy bodies of living Creatures are ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Empire of the Soul, and brought under its government and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Moreover, by means of them, the corporeal ſubſtance coheres with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporeal; whereby it comes to paſs, that they are as it were the Bands that tie both Soul and Body together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:103365:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Spirit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Spirit is an Airy, thin, tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Subſtance, the ſeat of natural Heat, the Vehicle of the Faculties, and the firſt Inſtrument that ſets the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions at work.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Spirits are there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two; the one innate, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther infus'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the innate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which was ingrafted into the ſeveral Similar Parts by the firſt Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Generation; the foundation of which is the <hi>Radical Moiſture.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the infus'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which flows in from elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, and cheriſhes and preſerves the innate, every where conveighing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and Heat, to enable the Functions in their ſeveral Duties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Threefold; Animal, Vital, and Natural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Animal Spirit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Spirit begat in the Ventricles of the Brain, of Vital Spirit, and inſpir'd Air; whence being diſtributed through
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:103365:29"/>the moving and ſenſitive Nerves, it renders all the Parts of the Body capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Sence and Motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Vital Spirit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is bred in the left part of the Heart, of the natural Spirit, and the Air ſuckt in by the Lungs, whence it is convey'd through the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries to every part, to cheriſh the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Spirit, corroborate the natural Heat, and reſtore ſtrength.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Natural Heat?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which proceeding from the Liver, is diffus'd together with the Bloud through all the Veins, the Cauſe of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, Nouriſhment and Growth.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Faculties.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus far we have diſcours'd of the Parts both Solid and Fluid, of Human Bodies; let us ſay ſomething concerning the Faculties and Functions of the Soul. Give me then the Definition of a Soul.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Soul is the form of a Living Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. By <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> it is defin'd the <hi>Ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lechy</hi> of a Natural, Organic Body, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentially having Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:103365:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is meant by <hi>Entelechia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Some interpret the Word to be the gaining of Perfection; others the Act of Perfection; but the latter Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation does not pleaſe me; for the Soul is not an <hi>Act,</hi> but the Efficient Cauſe of the Act. And thus Life is the Act of the Soul, not the Soul it ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Seeing then we are come to the conſideration of Man, I would have thee explain what the Soul of Man is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which gives him Vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, Senſual and Intellectual Life. By <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> it is defin'd, to be the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Living, Perceiving and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. By others, the firſt Cauſe of all the Functions of our Body, for the performance of which, it is endued with a manifold Ability or Faculty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Faculty;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the inbred power of the Soul, of which ſhe makes uſe for the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Actions. By <hi>Galen</hi> it is defin'd, The Efficient Cauſe of Actions; and is therefore a <hi>Faculty,</hi> becauſe whatever it does, it is able to do: ſo that under the Word <hi>Faculty</hi> is comprehended that which has a Power to act.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:103365:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why does <hi>Galen</hi> refer the Cauſe of Action to <hi>Temperament?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe Temperament is the <hi>Cauſe</hi> why the Soul performs her Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>without which ſhe could not.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſayes <hi>Galen,</hi> in his Book of <hi>Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturing by the Pulſes,</hi> The Soul is ſeated in the commodious Temperament of the ſeveral Parts; for that then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Part performs with vigor its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Office, when in beſt Temper. On the other ſide, it acts amiſs and feebly, when it is out of Temper.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Then the Soul it ſeems, flows from Temperament, unleſs you take the Soul to be Temperament it ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not believe the Soul to be Temperament, becauſe the Soul is a Subſtance; but Temperament is only an Accident: But I believe that <hi>Faculty</hi> flows from both; from the Soul, as from the Eſſential Form, which is the firſt and chief Cauſe of all thoſe Actions which we daily perform: from Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament, as from the accidental form, which is the aſſiſting Cauſe, without whoſe aid Souls cannot produce Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:103365:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Faculties are there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Eſſence of the Soul is purely uncompounded, becauſe there is but one form of one Body; but <hi>Faculty,</hi> by the Phyſicians is ſaid to be threefold; Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, Vital and Natural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Nature, the Architectreſs of the Body, when ſhe firſt begins to raiſe the Frame, bequeaths ſeveral <hi>Faculties</hi> to the ſingle Parts, for the preſervation of the whole; therefore there are as many Faculties of the Soul, as Parts of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Parts of the Body are endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed every one with their proper Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, on purpoſe to ſerve the whole with ſo many Actions which it cannot want; ſo that the number of Faculties and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganic Parts muſt be equal. But as the Parts, ſo the Faculties are contain'd under three Principal Kinds; Animal, Vital and Natural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Animal Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which is only enjoy'd by Animals; from whence it derives its Name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:103365:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is the Animal Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Animal Faculty is threefold; Principal, perceiving and moving.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the Principal Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which reſides only in the Brain, and in no other of the Organs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By <hi>Galen</hi> it it is ſaid to be three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold; Imagination, Ratiocination and Memory: But the firſt and laſt are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred only to the interior Senſe, by thoſe to whom the Underſtanding, only proper to Man, ſeems worthy the name of Principal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Imagination?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which receives and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the Images and Idea's of things objected to it, and accepted by the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; out of which being for the moſt part mixt and confus'd, it produces and forms many things which before fell not under the power of the ſenſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Ratiocination?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Mind is that with which Man endu'd, excels all other Creatures, by whoſe aſſiſtance it underſtands and knows things incorporeal, and forms
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:103365:32"/>abſtracted from all Matter; drawing univerſal Notions of things ſometimes out of one, ſometimes out of another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Memory?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which ſtores and lays up within it ſelf the forms and Images of Things repreſented by the Phanſie, and recall'd to the judgment of Reaſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Where are the Principal Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Soul lodg'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Arabians</hi> lodge the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the foremoſt Ventricles of the Brain, Reaſon in the middle, and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory in the hindermoſt; but the <hi>Grecks</hi> deny them to be confin'd to places, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming them to be diffus'd through all the corners, and over all the ſubſtance of the Brain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What think you of this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not like the Opinion of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> though grounded upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Arguments. <hi>Avicen</hi> and <hi>Aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes</hi> endeavour to demonſtrate that the Faculties have their diſtinct Seats from hence, becauſe that one of them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is deprav'd, without any hurt to the other; concluding thence the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probability
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:103365:32"/>that differing <hi>Faculties</hi> ſhould exiſt in the ſame Part of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. I confeſs indeed that many times one of the <hi>Faculties</hi> is deprav'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any harm to the other; for there is in <hi>Galen</hi> an excellent Story of <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi> who believ'd that the Muſicians were playing by his Bed-ſide, and order'd them to be put out of the Room, tho otherwiſe he talk'd rationally enough; ſo that there the Imagination was only deprav'd. There is another Story of a <hi>Lunatic,</hi> who having made faſt his doors, brought ſeveral Diſhes to the Window, which he call'd by ſeveral Names, asking every one that paſs'd by, whether they did command him to throw them away? Here the Reaſon was out of order. Another Story we find in <hi>Thueydides,</hi> of many, that while the Peſtilence raged in <hi>Greece,</hi> were ſo forgetful of every thing; that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew their own Parents nor Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance: Here the Memory was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deprav'd. But that proceeded from the various Conſtitution of the Body; for the Soul being pure and without mixture, according to the variety of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:103365:33"/>the Temperament, and ſtructure of the Inſtruments, cannot every where ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate alike, nor has an equal power in all things. Some we obſerve by Nature excelling in Wit and Imagination, tho of ſhallow Memories and Reaſon; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that have great Memories without Reaſon or Judgment; others to have a ſolid and natural Judgment, whoſe I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination is defective, and Memory but ſmall: ſo that it is no wonder to ſee ſome whoſe Imagination is diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd with a <hi>Delirium,</hi> their Memory and Reaſon untouch'd; for the ſtronger <hi>Faculty</hi> more powerfully reſiſts external Injuries, the weaker more eaſily yields. As therefore in one and the ſame Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle there are various natural Facuities, the attractive, retentive, concretive, and expulſive, of which one is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſturb'd, the other remaining ſound and unhurt, and yet no Phyſician will affirm them to be in ſeveral Seats, the ſame with <hi>Galen,</hi> I conclude, as to the Principal Faculties. Nevertheleſs the <hi>Arabians</hi> urge that Imagination is in the foremoſt, Reaſon in the middle, and Memory in the hinder Ventricles of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:103365:33"/>Brain, upon an Inference drawn from thence, That the foremoſt part of the Brain is ſofteſt, and more fit to receive Idea's; the hinder part harder, and more proper to retain the Notions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. But I deny the Conſequence, for what has been already ſaid; yet grant withal that the Principal Functions are more ſudden in their Actions in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Part of the Brain, in the hinder Part more perfect; becauſe the one is harder, the other ſofter: as we ſee, that if the whole ſubſtance of the Brain be ſomewhat dry, the Memory pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails; if moiſt, the Imagination; if temperate, the Judgment.</p>
                     <p>The followers of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> alſo further object, by the Teſtimony even of <hi>Galen</hi> himſelf, that there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cells, the one more noble then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as being the Seats of the more noble Faculties. But <hi>Galen</hi> prefers the hindmoſt Ventricle before the reſt, not that the Memory is there ſeated, the Reaſon in the middle, the Imagination in the foremoſt; but becauſe the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Reaſon are more imperfect in the foremoſt, the Memory more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:103365:34"/>in the middle, moſt perfect behind, becauſe there the Animal Spirit is brought to its Perfection.</p>
                     <p>They add, that <hi>Galen,</hi> the Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being deprav'd, apply'd Topic Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to the fore-part of the Head, as being the Seat of the Fancy: But they do not obſerve that <hi>Galen</hi> took the ſame courſe in all Affections of the Brain; as in Drowſineſs, the Apoplexy, Phren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Melancholy; not that the Seats of the <hi>Faculties</hi> were various, but to the end the force of the Medecine might penetrate more ſwiftly to the innermoſt Parts of the Brain, by reaſon of the thinneſs of the Scull, and the <hi>Coronal</hi> Cloſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt learnedly have you refuted the falſe Opinion of the <hi>Arabians,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Seat of the Principal <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</hi> Let us proceed to the Aſſiſtant <hi>Faculties.</hi> What is the ſenſible <hi>Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which from the Brain conveighs through the Nerves Senſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the whole Body by degrees.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Senſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Here it is taken Metonymically for the Act of feeling; but properly is a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:103365:34"/>Faculty diffus'd by the Animal Spirit, the ſenſitive Organ interceding, by which things ſenſible are perceiv'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is Senſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold. Interior and Exterior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the Interior Senſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which diſtinguiſhes the Objects of the ſeveral Exterior Senſes.</p>
                     <p>It is commonly call'd Common Senſe; for that all the External Senſes are ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed round about it, into whoſe Organs the Branches of the Nerves are diſperſt, by which the Soul powrs forth her Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy. the Primary Senſe, as King and Judge, has his Seat in the Body of the Brain, from whence, as from a Turret it contemplates all Idea's of things brought from without by the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring ſenſes, and obſerves all the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Senſes. <hi>Galen</hi> comprehends the Imagination under common Senſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the Exterior Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Five: Seeing, Hearing, Smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Taſting, Feeling.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Sight?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Senſe ſeated in the Eyes, which receives Colours through a <hi>Medium</hi> tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſpicuous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:103365:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What the Hearing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Senſe ſeated in the Ears, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Sounds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Smelling?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Senſe perceiving Scents convey'd through the Noſtrils.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Taſting?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Senſe reſiding in the Tongue, which judges of the ſeveral Taſts and Savors of things.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Feeling?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Senſe which being confin'd to no proper <hi>Organ,</hi> but equally diffus'd o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Body by the help of the Nerves, obſerves all tangible Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and their Differences, as Heat, Cold, Moiſture, Drineſs, Hardneſs, Softneſs, Roughneſs, Smoothneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the moving Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which gives motion to the Body, by the aſſiſtance of the Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, at the command of the Will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus far of the Animal Faculty. What is the Vital Faculty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is that which begets the Vital Faculty in the Heart, and diffuſes it eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way through the Arteries for the preſervation of Life; from whence it derives its Appellation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:103365:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Life?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Life is the continuance of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Heat glowing in the Primogeneal Moiſture, as Death is the extinction of that Vital Heat. By <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> Life is ſometimes defin'd, The Continuance of the Vegetable Soul in the Body; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Energy of an enliven'd Body. By others ſometimes it is ſaid to be the Union of the Soul with the Body; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the continuance of a Body enlive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Term, that it ceaſes to be: as Death is defin'd to be ſometimes the ſeparation of the Soul from the Organic Body; ſometimes the ſubſtantial Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of the enliven'd Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many <hi>Faculties</hi> are ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the <hi>Vital Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two: Reſpiration, and Beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Pulſes; becauſe the Vital Spirit is bred and diſtributed by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of Reſpiration and the Pulſes: But as Reſpiration conſiſts of Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Expiration, ſo the Pulſe by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation and Contraction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Does not the Iraſcible <hi>Faculty,</hi> by the Philoſophers plac'd in the Heart, belong to the Vital?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:103365:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe the Iraſcible Faculty is that by which the Heart is mov'd to proſecute that which is good, as to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void that which is evil, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Life, not only that, but the Concupiſcible Faculty, by which the Heart is mov'd to embrace that which is good, is alſo to be referr'd to the <hi>Vital Faculty.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> as they aſſign the iraſcible Faculty to the Heart, ſo they appropriate the concupiſcible to the Liver.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Galen</hi> there by the concupiſcible Faculty does not mean that Deſire by which a man is carry'd with apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion toward the Object, but the natural Appetite after Nouriſhment, which, tho it be fix'd in every part, yet he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribes it to the Liver, as being the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular place where the Bloud is made.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Natural Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which being convey'd from the Liver through the Veins, affords Nouriſhment to all Parts of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three: That which nouriſhes, that which cauſes growth, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Faculty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:103365:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Nouriſhing Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>That which converts and aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates the receiv'd Nouriſhment to the ſubſtance of the body. It alſo reſtores the continual decays of the body, and remains to the laſt day of Life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many <hi>Faculties</hi> are ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to the <hi>Nouriſhing Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Four: The Attractive, Reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Concording, and Expulſive.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Attractive?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which covets and draws to every Part convenient Moiſture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Retentive?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which retains the attracted Nouriſhment till the Altering Faculty have chang'd it into the Nature of that Part which it is deſign'd to nouriſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Concoctive Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which alters the attracted and retain'd Nouriſhment, changes, concocts it, applies and aſſimilates it to the Part which is to be nouriſhed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Expulſive?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which ſeparates and expels that which is not proper for Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſuperfluous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:103365:37"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Increaſing Faculty;</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which extends and enlarges the body till the time appointed by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Generative Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which begets its own like: But that is not ſimple, but compounded of two Faculties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are thoſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Changing and Forming Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Changing Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which changes the firſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance out of which Generation is made, and converts it into that proper and convenienter Matter which is to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Forming Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which makes the Form a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the whole and every Part of the body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus far of the Animal, Vital and Natural Faculties. But is the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual conſent of all requir'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are ſo far conjoyn'd by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Conſent, ſaith <hi>Fernelius,</hi> that every one ſingly ſubſiſts by the help of the reſt. The Vital perfects the reſt, and ſets
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:103365:37"/>them at work, and is by them aſſiſted by mutual Kindneſſes. The Natural af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords it food; the Animal by the motion of the Breaſt and Lungs, is the Cauſe of Nouriſhment and Refrigerarion.</p>
                     <p>To the Animal the other two afford Matter, and the Vital running through the Arteries, preſerves and increaſes it, which always her ſelf ſtands in need of the Animal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which by mutual Conſent of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors is the agreed Order of the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By the order of Procreation, the Natural is firſt, then the Vital, and the Animal laſt: But in order of Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, the Animal precedes, then the Vital, and laſtly the Natural: But as to the Neceſſity of Life and Action, the Vital is the firſt of all, then the Natural, and laſt of all the Animal.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Action.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>After the Faculties follow the Actions. What is an Action?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>An Action is a Motion proceeding
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:103365:38"/>a Faculty; ſometimes from the <hi>Greek</hi> call'd <hi>Energy;</hi> from the <hi>Latins, Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or Operation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How is <hi>Function</hi> divided?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As Faculty is threefold, ſo is <hi>Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> Animal, Vital, and Natural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But <hi>Galen</hi> allows but two ſorts of <hi>Functions</hi> Animal and Natural. Of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſaies he, there are two primary Differences; for ſome are the Actions of the Soul, and others of Nature: therefore the firſt are call'd Animal, and the ſecond Natural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I Anſwer, That in that place <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> comprehends the Vital under the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimal <hi>Functions.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How do the Intellectual Actions differ from the Senſible?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>There is this particular difference between them, That the Senſible Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have every one their particular Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, by which they are committed; Sight, the Eye; Hearing, the Ear; the Action of Smelling, the Noſe; Taſt, the Tongue; Feeling, the Skin: But Intellectual Actions want the help of no Corporeal Organ, becauſe they are not capable of Corporeity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:103365:38"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>As if the Brain were not the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan of the Functions of the Mind, whoſe Temperament is ſo neceſſary for the true performances of Underſtanding, Cogitation, and Ratiocination; that that being once deprav'd, Phrenſie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I grant the Brain to be the Organ of Imagination, which contains the Idea's of Corporeal things, but not of the Mind, only ſo far, as that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not operate in the Body, without the help of ſenſible Idea's.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are voluntary Actions divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are twofold; ſome are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually free, others ſubject to the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are altogether free;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe which we do perpetually, when and as often as we pleaſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any impediment, as Speaking and Walking.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are ſubject to the Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as are not perpetual, but at certain times, as the Neceſſities of the Body require; as making Water, and Eaſement of the Belly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:103365:39"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are the Vital Functions di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Of the Vital Actions, the one is the principal, which is the work of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Vital Spirit, two Miniſterial, as Reſpiration, and the beating of the Pulſes. Under the <hi>Pulſatii</hi> Actions are comprehended the Motions of the heart, proceeding from the iraſcible and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcible Faculties: From the one Glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Hope, Love, which dilate the Heart, as embracing the Object of Good. From the other, Sadneſs, Fear, Hatred, by which the Heart is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, troubled and oppreſs'd, as avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the evil Object.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Is Reſpiration an Animal or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Action?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a voluntary Action, being made by the help of the Muſcles, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracting and dilating the Breaſt, but not altogether free, becauſe it is done upon Neceſſity. Others believe Reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to be a mixt Action, partly Animal, in reſpect of the Organs; partly Natural, as depending upon the motion of the Heart, which is Natural; and becauſe it never ceaſes whether we ſleep or wake,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:103365:39"/>when all the Animal Actions ceaſe in Sleep.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Is the Pulſe an Animal or Natural Motion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Pulſe neither depends upon the Will, nor Nature ſimply, but upon the Vital Faculty of the Soul, which is Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural. Not upon the Will, becauſe we cannot make this motion, nor ſtop it at our own pleaſures. Not ſimply upon Nature; for nothing moves in a living Body but the Soul: for otherwiſe there would be more then one form, The Soul is of an Animal Nature, which to preſerve its Union with the Body, moves the Heart, concocts in the Stomach and Liver, and performs all the other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Life. Therefore the Pulſe is a Natural motion of the Heart proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Natural Faculty of the Soul, which is not voluntary, but vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many Actions proceed from the <hi>Natural Faculty?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Nutritive, increaſing, and generative Faculties.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Nutrition?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Nutrition is the converſion of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:103365:40"/>receiv'd Aliment into the ſubſtance of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How is Nutrition brought to paſs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That ſame Juice, which being to nouriſh every part of the Body, falls from the Veſſels, is firſt diſpers'd into every part, then apply'd, and aggluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, and after that aſſimilated; ſo that Nutrition is a perfect Aſſimilation; but that Aſſimilation may be brought to paſs, Agglutination muſt precede, and before that Application.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Aſſiſtants of Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Attraction, Retention, Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Expulſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are theſe Actions brought to perfection?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are all, except Concoction, brought to perfection by the help of the Fibres; Attraction by the aid of the ſtreight Fibres; Retention, of the oblique; and Expulſion by the aſſiſtance of the tranſverſe: For as the Muicles, contracted at our will and pleaſure, and as it were reduc'd to their Original, cauſe Motion, ſo it happens to the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:103365:40"/>Inſtruments; that by the ſtreight fibres through the only inſtinct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture contracted, the Nouriſhment is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted; by the tranſverſe fibres con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, whatever lay in the more roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my ſpace, is by that contraction ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd. But becauſe the oblique fibres being ſtretch'd forth, admit neither of a ſhorter or narrower capacity, Nature obſerving a kind of equality and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, they contain every thing, and neither attract nor expel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How is Concoction perfected?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>By the innate Heat alone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Concoction can you reckon?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three: The firſt in the Stomach, the ſecond in the Liver, and the third in the ſeveral Parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Increaſing?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the enlargement of the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Parts into length, breadth, and depth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Generation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the Production of a new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; therefore it is not a ſimple acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nature, but compounded of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Formation. By theſe two
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:103365:41"/>Actions all Generation is brought to perfection: For when any ſubſtance is changed into another, it ſuffers a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of its proper Eſſence; as when out of the procreative Seed and Bloud, a Bone, or a Nerve, or any other Part is generated; being withall faſhion'd into the ſhape agreeable to Nature. But this Function then chiefly acts it part, when the Birth lies in the Womb.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The <hi>Dean's</hi> Judgment of the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didate's</hi> Merit.</head>
                  <p>In this Phyſiological Examination, <hi>Candidate,</hi> Thou haſt given us ſuch a Specimen of thy Learning and Induſtry, that if thou anſwer'ſt my Fellow-Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giates that are to diſpute with thee, ſo accurately and acutely as to the other Parts of Phyſic, I judge thee worthy <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Lawrel.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="disputation">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:103365:41"/>
               <head>THE SECOND DISPUTATION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Things not Natural; in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of which, that Part of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſic which concerns the Method of preſerving Health, conſiſts.</p>
               </argument>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
                  <p>HAving made and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of Natural Things, we are now to proceed to things not Natural. What are Things not Natural?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>Such as preſerve the Natural Conſtitution of Man?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Why are they ſo call'd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe they are not of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man, nor againſt his Nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:103365:42"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How many things not Natural are there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Six in Number: The ambient Air, Meat and Drink, Sleep and Waking, Motion and Reſt, Expulſion and Reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Paſſions of the Mind; in the true Uſe of which conſiſts the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of Preſerving Health.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Are they all neceſſary to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Man's Body?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>So neceſſary, that without the uſe of every one, Human Life cannot ſubſiſt. For in regard there is a continual waſte of our threefold ſubſtance by the innate Heat, there is a neceſſity of reſtoring the ſpirituous by Air, of the ſolid by Meat, and of the humid by Drink. Sleep is alſo neceſſary for the Concocti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Nutriment, and to reinforce the waſted Spirits. It is neceſſary we ſhould wake, that the functions of the Soul may have liberty to act. Exerciſe is neceſſary to excite the Natural Heat. Alternate Reſt is requiſite to relieve the Members weary'd by Labour: And in regard that Nature is not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert all the Nouriſhment we receive into the ſubſtance of the Body, is is but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:103365:42"/>that the Excrements ſhould be expell'd, And the Paſſions of the Mind cannot be avoyded in regard of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Good and Evil.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherein conſiſts the Method of preſerving Health?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>In the convenient Quality, Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, Manner and Time of uſing the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things not Natural.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Ambient Air.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Air is to be choſen to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a ſound Health?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such an Air as is neither too fat nor thick, nor miſty by reaſon of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning Lakes or Rivers; but thin and ſerene; neither over-hot, nor over-moiſt, nor over-cold, nor over-dry; but temperate; not infected with the exhalations of ſtanding Waters, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Sewers, nor Church-Yards; nor defil'd with Dunghils, or the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſtench of things either ſuperior or inferior, nor in a Vally ſurrounded with high Mountains, or in any hollow place where the Wind has no power.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:103365:43"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How much Air is requiſite for a man to draw?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Strong People, the more Breath they fetch, the better they are in health; but for weak Perſons, and ſuch are new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recover'd from Sickneſs, to remove out of a cloſe, into a free and open Air, is dangerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are they then to order them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the uſe of Air?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They muſt by degrees and inſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly accuſtom themſelves to a more free and plentiful Air.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When may they moſt ſafely op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to a freer Air?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon ſerene days, when the Air is neither too hot with the Sun-Beams, nor over-cold, and the Wind is not too high.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Meat and Drink.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſort of Meat is to be made choice of, for the preſervation of Health?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which conſiſts of good Juice, eaſie of Digeſtion, and which contains
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:103365:43"/>the leaſt Excrement. On the other ſide, Meat whoſe Juice is evil, hard of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and abounding with excrement, is to be avoided.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Meat is that which affords good Juice?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which is neither hotter nor colder, nor drier nor moiſter then it ſhould be, but temperate; neither too glutinous, nor too thin; for ſuch food breeds Blood of a laudable temperature and conſiſtence, neither too thick, nor too ſerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How much food is to be taken?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>So much as may ſuffice to reſtore the waſted ſubſtance of the Body; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they who abound with natural heat, and uſe much exerciſe, becauſe they make a great waſte of their ſubſtance, need a larger ſupply of food. On the other ſide, they whoſe natural heat is weak, and live at eaſe, ought to be moderate in eating; and the more plain and ſimple the Diet is, ſo much the more familiar to Nature. And as Sobriety is moſt wholeſom, ſo plenty and variety of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals clogs and tires the Stomach.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What method is to be obſerv'd in eating?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:103365:44"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Meat before it be ſwallow'd, ought to be very well chew'd by the Teeth. And there is this order to be obſerv'd in feeding, that the liquid muſt precede the ſolid, the light the heavy, and the looſning the binding victuals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When is the beſt time to feed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A man ought to feed at a ſet hour, the firſt being concocted and deſcended into his Belly; having before us'd ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient exerciſe, and the Appetite calling for it, that Nature, which does her Work at a prefix'd time, may the more chearfully attend the work of Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſort of Drink is beſt for the preſervation of Health?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Of all ſorts of Drink, Wine is chiefly to be commended; but ſomewhat red, ſometimes white, clear, thin, not ſweet, not ſharp, fine, and rather ſmall, then too ſtrong; with a larger quantity of Water in the Summer, then in the Winter: But to men of hot tempers, Water is more convenient then Wine; of which the beſt is the cleareſt and lighteſt, without the leaſt ill ſcent or ſavour. Sider and Perry is better then
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:103365:44"/>Water, Ale and Beer well brew'd of Barly-water and Hops, for thoſe Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that live in the North Parts, is a good ſort of Drink, ſo it be clear, thin, and neither too new, mor too ſmall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How much Drink is ſufficient?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>So much as is anſwerable to the Meat receiv'd. Solid and dry Diet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more liberal drinking; for li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid and moiſt Meats, more moderate drinking will ſuffice: But as for Wine, if it be immoderately taken, it tears up the ſtrength of Body and Mind, and haſtens Old Age.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the method of Drinking?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Too much Drink at Meals, cauſes the Meat to float in the Stomach; nor is it good to drink too ſparingly, for that ſuffices not to quench thirſt; and frequent drinking between Meals, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Concoction; but all Drink whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Wine or Ale, made cooler either by Water, Snow, or Nitre, to cool the Summer-heat, is to be avoided as pernicious to the Nerves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When is it proper to drink at Meals?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As Hunger argues a neceſſity of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:103365:45"/>eating, ſo Thirſt implies a neceſſity of drinking, to ſupply the Radical Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture. But though a man be not adry when he has eaten the half of the ſolid meat he intends, it is yet then good to drink, to mix and moiſten it in the Stomach, by which means it may be the more eaſily digeſted, and convey'd to the Liver; for that Drink is the Vehicle of the Meat: But before Meat, and preſently after Meals, after Bathing, or while a man is in a Sweat, all drinking is to be forborn.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Sleeping and Waking.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Sleep is requiſite for the Health of the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Quiet, ſound and moderate; for that Sleep is not commendable, which is diſturb'd with reſtleſs Dreams; nor ſo ſlight, as to be diſturb'd with the leaſt noiſe; worſt of all immoderate ſleep; for it hinders the due expulſion of the Excrements out of the Body, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains them beyond their time; it begets abundance of Superfluities, renders the Brain more cold and moiſt, breeds the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:103365:45"/>Head-Ach, and cauſes Drownineſs of the Mind, and Dulneſs of the Senſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How long time may a man be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd for Sleep?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Of this Judgment is to be made from the perfect Concoction of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements; for no certain time can be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to all perſons, in regard that ſome concoct ſooner, ſome later. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever for the moſt part, ſix, ſeven, or eight hours at moſt is to be allotted for the time of ſleep: But for the determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the proportion of ſleep, we muſt conſider the Temper, Age, Nouriſhment received, and Labour the perſon has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> more Sleep then the Flegmatic, Old men than Young men, they that feed more liberally, then they that feed ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly; and they that have labour'd either with Body or Mind, then they that have uſed none.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the beſt way for a man to lie when he takes his reſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Let a man lie firſt upon his right ſide, that his Meat may deſcend more quickly to the bottom of his Stomach; then upon his left, that by the Stomach's
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:103365:46"/>reſting toward the Liver, Concoction may be forwarded; which done, let him turn again upon his right ſide, that the <hi>Chylus</hi> may be more eaſily diſtributed to the Liver. Add to this, that the ſhift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſides in this manner, does not a little refreſh the wearineſs of the Body. Lying upon the Back is condemned by all, as being the occaſion of many Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes; and lying upon the face is bad for thoſe who are troubled with deflucti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What time is moſt wholeſom for Sleep?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The moſt convenient time is the Night, two or three hours after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; the Night being moſt fit for Sleep, by reaſon of its Moiſture and Tranqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: Beſides, that it affords time enough to perfect the Concoction of the Meat, there being no occaſion for a man to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb his through exigency of buſineſs. On the other ſide, ſleeping by day is moſt pernicious, becauſe it fills the Brain with too much moiſture, which ought rather to be dried up by waking.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Waking is moſt whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:103365:46"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As moderate Sleep is wholeſom, immoderate hurtful, the ſame is to be ſaid of waking; for as too much Sleep over-cools and moiſtens the Brain, ſo exceſs of waking weakens the Temper of the Brain, debilitates the Senſes, hinders Concoction, and begets Gru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities; for that while a man wakes, the Natural Heat together with the Bloud and Spirit, keeps out in the external parts. ſo that as the Night is the ſeaſon for Sleep, ſo is the Day for Waking: Wherefore it was the Precept of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> to ſleep by night, and wake by day; for the night cauſes a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, and the day a better diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Nouriſhment, and expulſion of Excrements: Beſides the Animal Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is more encourag'd to labour in her Functions by the heat and light of the Day.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Exerciſe.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Exerciſe is requiſite?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Not too eaſie, nor too vehement; not too ſwift, nor too ſlow; but mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: However the Flegmatic require
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:103365:47"/>a ſtronger and more violent Exerciſe then the Choleric. Equality in Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is preferr'd before Inequality: And that Exerciſe which moſt delights the Mind, ought to be look'd upon as the moſt wholeſom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How long is Exerciſe to be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Till the Body grow warm, and a lively Colour appear in the Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, together with a Sweat mix'd with a hot Vapour; till the Reſpiration be large, yet eaſie; and while the Motion continues equal and brisk. While any of theſe fail, 'tis time to deſiſt, leſt the Body grow colder, drier and leaner with long exerciſe: But always let the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of the perſon be anſwerable to his Food; for the more liberally or ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly a man feeds, the more or leſs he ought to exerciſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the method of Exerciſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Exerciſe is requiſite as often as the Body is fed; a gentle motion at firſt, then more vehement, then more gentle again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What time is moſt fit for Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:103365:47"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Concoction is perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But in regard that Exerciſe ſtirs up the Natural Heat, without which, the Meat cannot well be concocted; Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ought to be always us'd before Meals: Beſides that, Exerciſe conſumes many Superfluities, which are firſt to be expell'd, before any more Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be receiv'd in. After Meals Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe is hurtful, in regard the agitation of the Body joggs down the Nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of the Stomach ere it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted, which occaſions ſeveral Crudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the Veins, that beget ſeveral Diſeaſes. Neither is a man to exerciſe, till he has emptied his Body of ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements as call upon Nature, leſt any thing of them be carried away into the Habit of the Body, through the force of the Natural Heat redoubled by Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Reſt.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>When is Reſt required?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Body is wearied with extraordinary motion; for in all moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body, ſays <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> when any perſon comes to be wearied, Reſt
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:103365:48"/>is preſently the Remedy againſt Weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. This <hi>Ovid</hi> alſo confirms, where he ſays, That whatever wants alternate Reſt, can never long ſupport it ſelf; for Reſt repairs the ſtrength, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creates the weary Members. The Mind alſo wearied with Cares and ſtudy, ſtands in need of Relaxation and Reſt, which unleſs you grant, it is impoſſible to maintain its Vigor.</p>
                     <p>Eaſe nouriſhes the Body, and feeds the Mind. But as moderate Eaſe is wholeſom, ſo immoderate Sloth is hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for it dulls the vigor of the Mind, and begets Crudity: For as by Exerciſe the Native Heat is increas'd, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction expedited, ſo is it by Sloth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh'd, and Concoction hinder'd.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Excrements.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Excrements are whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſeveral Excrements if they be moderate, and ſeaſonably thrown off, are wholeſom; but if they be kept in, and tarry too long in the Body, they putrefie, and breed ſeveral ſorts of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes:
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:103365:48"/>Wherefore for the preſervation of Health they are to be expell'd in time by the help of Art.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But artificial evacuation is not convenient, becauſe we learn out of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates,</hi> That ſane People purg'd by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thartick Med'cins, ſuddenly decay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That is to be underſtood of ſuch as are of an unblameable habit of Body, who before Meals are conſtant in their exerciſe of their Body and Mind, and take an accurate care in obſerving due Concoction. But as for them who keep no conſtant method of Feeding, or through Intemperance, or Buſineſs, or Ignorance, tho healthy and ſtrong, they cannot pretend to be ſafe from Diſeaſes, unleſs it be by a provident looſning the Belly by intervals, or ſometimes by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of more powerful Purgation, and by ſeaſonable opening a Vein, or taking ſuch Remedies as are effectual to concoct, attenuate, and cleanſe, as <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> tells us in his Book <hi>De Euchymia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is to be obſerv'd in deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Quantity of Evacuation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>You are always to conſider the ſtrength of the Perſon; for all Evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:103365:49"/>too exceſſive, is dangerous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it weak'ns the ſtrength.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the method of Evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Where there is moſt ſuperfluous Matter, there by little and little, not all at once evacuation is to be made, leſt the Body be too ſuddenly and too vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently weak'nd; therefore it is better to let Bloud often, then to take away too much at one time. In the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it is ſafe to purge the Body by mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate reiteration, then to give a Scowrer all at once. Thus it is better to procure Sweat, Urine, or Womens Flowers by gentle reiterated Med'cins, then by one forcible Medicament. And thus the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate Uſe of the Venereal Act with due ceſſation, may be wholſom for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, whereas the immoderate uſe of it, is the deſtruction of Health.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the fitteſt time for Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As for the Seaſon of the Year, the Spring is the fitteſt for Bloud-letting and Purging, according to the Opinion of <hi>Hippocrates;</hi> for then, ſaith <hi>Philotheus,</hi> the Heat is neither too fierce, which
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:103365:49"/>a Diſſolution of the Body, nor the Cold too vehement, which thickens the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors. <hi>Galen</hi> alſo preſcribes the Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation of ſuperfluous Humors in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumn, by way of Precaution. Now for the Excrements which are hurtful in themſelves, as the Excrement of the Guts, Urine, Sweat, Snot, and Spittle, they are daily to be evacuated; but ſuch as are only hurtful in their Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, as the Seed and Menſtruous Bloud, they may be retain'd till their Quantity offend.</p>
                     <p>Moderate Coition after the firſt Sleep is moſt profitable, as well for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of Health, as for Generation: for then the Seed is perfectly concocted, and the loſs of Spirits is eaſily made good again by the enſuing Sleep. Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, during the coming down of the Monthly Courſes, is prohibited, for fear the Birth prove Leprous; nor is it good upon a full or a faſting Stomach. The Spring is the moſt proper ſeaſon, and Youth the moſt proper Age for it. In other Ages of men, the Seed is either none at all, or elſe unfit for Generation. If the Flowers come not down, they
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:103365:50"/>are to be provok'd by Art, at the ſame time that uſually they came down before. But neither Women with Child, nor Nurſes, nor young Girles, nor Old Women are permitted to make uſe of Art in that particular.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the Paſſions of the Mind.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of all the things not Natural, which belong to the preſervation of Health, there only remain thoſe which the <hi>Latins</hi> call Perturbations of the Mind. I deſire thee to explain what and how many they are, and whether they be wholeſom or no?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Paſſions are Motions of the Mind, violent, and contrary to right Reaſon, which cauſe an alteration in the Body, becauſe of the extraordinary force of the Native Heat acting together with the Spirit and Bloud, both without and within. There are four Principal Paſſions; two ariſing from an Opinion of a good Object, as Gladneſs, or Joy and Deſire; and as many out of an appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a bad Object, as Sadneſs and Fear. Anger and Shame are added; but
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:103365:50"/>the firſt being a burning Deſire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, is referr'd to Deſire, as the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may be ſaid to relate to Fear.</p>
                     <p>The two firſt ſorts of Paſſion, if they be moderate, are wholeſom, otherwiſe pernicious: For many puſilanimous Perſons have expir'd through immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Joy, as the Writings of ſeveral Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors teſtifie; but all the reſt are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for many have di'd through vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſudden grief: at what time a weak little Soul being oppreſs'd by a ſtrong Affection, was preſently extinct, and ſuffocated, while all the Bloud was violently carry'd away to make an inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation upon its firſt Original. Thus <hi>Pliny</hi> relates, that P. <hi>Rutilius,</hi> hearing the News of his Brothers Repulſe upon his putting in for the Conſulſhip, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently expir'd. Thus upon the 16th. of <hi>August</hi> 1619. <hi>Monteler,</hi> a Noble young Gentleman of <hi>Tours,</hi> and Lieutenant Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Ments,</hi> through extraordinary Grief fell down ſuddenly dead, as he was talking in the Street: His Body being open'd, all his Bowels appear'd to be ſound, only we obſerv'd his <hi>Pericardium</hi> to be full not
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:103365:51"/>only of Water, but a great quantity of thick Bloud, which upon ſome vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment motion foregoing, the Heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contracted through extream Grief, had made its way through the two Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and ſuddenly ſuffocated the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Life, whence follow'd ſudden Death. Through Fear alſo the Spirits and Bloud are drawn back to their firſt Fountain, whence it comes to paſs, that the Parts wax cold, the Countenance grows pale, the Body quivers, Utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance fails, and the force and ſtrength of the whole Frame grows weak and faint. On the other ſide, in Anger the motion of the Natural Heat is more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement, which at length throws it ſelf forth with violence into the outmoſt parts. From whence the Countenance becomes red, and the whole Body being warm, becomes more bold, and ready to put it ſelf forth into danger. In Shame both the inner and outer Parts ſuffer; becauſe the Heat firſt flies to the inner Parts, and then throws it ſelf forth again. Seeing then the force of the Perturbations of the Mind is ſo great it behoves the Phyſician to correct or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them by all the Art imaginable.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="disputation">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:103365:51"/>
               <head>THE THIRD DISPUTATION <hi>Of Things Preter-Natural;</hi> In the Knowledge of <hi>Pathology,</hi> employs it ſelf.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
                  <p>THus far of things Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and not Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; it remains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind to treat of things Preternatural. What are Preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cand.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe things which deſtroy the Natural Conſtitution of the Body of Man, are call'd Affections, or ſuch Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures of Evil under which the Body ſuffers; which being by the <hi>Greeks</hi> call'd <hi>Pathe,</hi> therefore the Learning which handles theſe Affections, is call'd <hi>Patho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:103365:52"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How many Preternatural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>Three: The Diſeaſe, the Cauſe, and the Symptom. In regard that every Affection of the Body receding from its natural Conſtitution, is either a Diſeaſe, or the Cauſe of Diſeaſe, or a Symptom; as <hi>Galen</hi> teſtifies, <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>De Diff. Symp.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D.</speaker>
                  <p>How are they diſtinguiſh'd one from another?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>That Affection which hinders the Action, is call'd a Diſeaſe; if any thing follow this, a Symptom; that which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions it, the Cauſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Diſeaſes.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Diſeaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Diſeaſe is a Preternatural Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection by which the Action is firſt harm'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I thus diſpute againſt it: Every Diſeaſe is not a Diſpoſition; therefore is ill defin'd by <hi>Galen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I deny the Antecedent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D,</speaker>
                     <p>I prove it thus: For the moſt part a Diſeaſe is a Habit; but Diſpoſition is
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:103365:52"/>not a Habit; yea, it is oppos'd to Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> becauſe Habit is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Quality which cannot eaſily be remov'd from the Subject; but Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is a Quality that may be eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd from the Subject.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word Diſpoſition, that is, Affection, is underſtood by <hi>Galen,</hi> not according to that more ſpecial ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein Diſpoſition, that is a preparation to Habit, is us'd by <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle;</hi> but according to the more general ſignification, under which he compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends Diſpoſition and Habit: for ſome Diſeaſes eaſily come, and ſoon go off; others are with difficulty remov'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Moreover, by this Argument I prove that the Diſeaſe does not in the firſt place injure the Action. Faculty differs from Action, as the Cauſe from the Effect; but the Diſeaſe firſt injures the Faculty; therefore the Action is not firſt injur'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That is falſe in an Organic Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper; for the Uſe of the Inſtrument may be hinder'd without any injury to the Faculty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:103365:53"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>However in a ſimilar Diſeaſe the Faculty is injur'd before the Action.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, A Phyſician makes his Judgment of all things according to Senſe: but we do not find the Faculty hurt, before we find the Action fail.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides I thus prove, That every Diſeaſe does not injure the Action: A Wound is a Diſeaſe, but the Functions of the wounded Part remain entire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it attracts, retains, aſſimilates the Bloud, and laſtly, reſtores the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Fleſh cut off: There every Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe does not injure the Action.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I Anſwer, theſe things are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the found part, which are next to the Wound.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many general Diviſions are there of a Diſeaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Diſeaſe is threefold; Similar, Organic, and Common.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Similar Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Diſtemper which firſt injures the Action of the Similar Part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is either Simple or Compound. A Simple Diſtemper is either hot, cold,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:103365:53"/>moiſt, or dry. The Compound Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per is either hot and moiſt, hot and dry, cold and moiſt, cold and dry; at that either alone, or joyn'd with Matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is an Organic Diſtemper?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Diſproportion of the Structure which firſt injures the uſe of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is fourfold; either in the form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Magnitude, the Number or Situation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Diſeaſe of Form?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diſeaſe of Form is, when the natural Figure of the Frame is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd, or when a Paſſage or Cavity is dilated beyond meaſure, or ſtreightn'd, or obſtructed where it ſhould not be; or when the Part is rough where it ſhould be ſmooth, or ſmooth where it ſhould be rough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Diſeaſe of Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diſeaſe of Magnitude is when any Part is increa'sd or diminiſh'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond or beneath its due proportion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Diſeaſe of Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:103365:54"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Diſeaſe of Number is when any Part is wanting or ſuperabounds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Diſeaſe of Situa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When any Part looſens from its proper place, as when the Kall or great Gut falls into the Scrotum.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Common Diſeaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſeparation of the Continuity, which hinders the Functions of both parts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is the ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Continuity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Fourfold: A Wound, an Ulcer, a Fracture, a putting out of Joynt: which may be likewiſe call'd a Diſeaſe in Situation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why do you here omit a Tumor againſt Nature?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe a Tumor preternatural is ſaid to be a compounded Diſeaſe of Diſtemper, ill Figure, and ſeparation of the Continuity, by a Word from the <hi>Greek</hi> call'd an <hi>Apoſteme.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſignifications will the Word <hi>Apoſteme</hi> bear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two: The one General, and the other Special; for generally the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:103365:54"/>Word <hi>Aposteme</hi> is taken for any Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor which is preternatural; but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for an Inflammation brought to Suppuration; and many times for a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, wherein ſome certain Matter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Veſicle, reſembling Honey or Greaſe, or thick Grewel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Where do theſe Apoſtemes breed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>In the extream Parts of the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>There 'tis true they uſe to breed, but we obſerv'd not long ſince a new place which they had found out, never heard of before in the Schools of the Phyſicians.</p>
                     <p>The moſt Illuſtrious, the Marqueſs of <hi>Monte-pezzati,</hi> a Perſon of a ſharp Wit, upon the ceaſing of a Dyſentery, to which he had been ſubject from his younger years, and after a ſuppreſſion of the Emrods, which for eight years together had kept their conſtant courſe, in the 49th. year of his Age, 1619. he was taken at <hi>Tours</hi> with a violent and obſtinate pain in the Head, the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of which was a <hi>Delirium.</hi> All the Remedies that the moſt Famous Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of <hi>Tours</hi> could imagine, were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, but all to no purpoſe: wherefore
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:103365:55"/>he was remov'd to <hi>Preſſignac,</hi> at a good diſtance from the King's Court, whither I was call'd, together with three other of the moſt eminent, to try our Skill; but notwithſtanding all the moſt violent Remedies that could be rationally us'd, not being able to vanquiſh the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, at length he dy'd Lethargic.</p>
                     <p>His Body being open'd under the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt right-ſide Ventricle, a part of it was apparently corrupted, in which there appear'd various and ſundry forms of an Apoſteme, the Veſicles of which were about the bigneſs of a Pine-Nut. This Obſervation I thought fit to give thee an accompt of by the way. Now let us return to the General Diſcourſe of <hi>Apostemes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts are Tumors pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternatural?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Fourfold: <hi>Phlegmone, Eryſipelas, Oedema</hi> and <hi>Skirrus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is <hi>Phlegmone?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a Tumor preternatural, caus'd by the Bloud ſtarting out of the Veins, and dilating the Part with Heat, Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Paint, Beating, and reſiſting the Touch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:103365:55"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is an <hi>Eryſipelas?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>An Inflammation very hot lying in the Skin, and ſometimes incroaching upon the Fleſh underneath, proceeding from a Choleric hot Blood, which by reaſon of its thinneſs cauſes no great Swelling, but diſperſes it ſelf in length and breadth every way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is an <hi>Oedema?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A cold, looſe, white Tumor, void of pain, leaving the print of the finger that touches it, proceeding from a Phlegmatic Humor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a <hi>Skirrhus?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A hard, reſiſting Tumor, void of pain, with little or no ſence of feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, proceeding from a Melancholy Humor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a <hi>Wound?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a new ſeparation of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiguity in ſoft parts by ſome Cut, Bite, or other external Accident.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is an <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lcer?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſeparation of the Continuity in ſoft parts, made by Corroſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a <hi>Fracture?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the Union of the Bone ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; occaſioned by ſome external Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:103365:56"/>bruiſing or breaking the ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Luxation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the falling or ſlipping of a Joynt out of its proper place into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the impeding the voluntary Motion.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Morbific Cauſes.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is here meant by the word <hi>Cauſe?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>An Affection againſt Nature, which cauſes the Diſeaſe; the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of which, is call'd <hi>Aetiology.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>The Cauſe of a Diſeaſe is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſubſtantial, as ſome Humor or Wind, or ſomething elſe preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral; as, a Stone; but Affection is a Quality; therefore Affection is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the cauſe of a Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word Affection is otherwiſe us'd by <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> that is, for every thing that is able to deſtroy the natural Temper and Structure of the Body, and injure its Actions, whether it be Subſtance or Quality.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:103365:56"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts are Morbiſic Cauſes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold: Internal and Exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the Internal Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which reſides within the Body.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold: the preceding and containing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the Antecedent Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which nouriſhes the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many kinds?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two: Plethoric and Cacochymic.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the <hi>Plethora?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A Redundancy of all the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors equally augmented; or elſe a redundancy of the Blood alone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many kinds are there of <hi>Plethora?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two: the one in reſpect of the Strength; the other in reſpect of the Veſſels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:103365:57"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a <hi>Plethora</hi> in reſpect of the Strength?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Blood neither in quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity nor quality exceeding due meaſure, yet oppreſſes the Strength debilitated by ſome other Cauſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a <hi>Plethora</hi> as to the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Humor exceeds its due meaſure; which is either light, when it only fills the Cavity of the Veins, and only exceeds proportion by a little, or diſtenſive, when it diſtends and almoſt rends the Tunicles of the Veins.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How does the <hi>Plethora</hi> in reſpect of the Veſſels, and that other in reſpect of the Strength differ?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When during the <hi>Plethora</hi> the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy waxes heavy, yet the Strength of all parts remains equal, only there is a fulneſs of the Veſſels. But if the Body and the Arteries wax heavy, and the motion grows ſlow, if a drowſie, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd and unquiet Sleep follow, and the Patient complain of being oppreſs'd by ſome weight, or that he carries ſome burden, or dream he cannot be remov'd out of his place, then it is an over-ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs oppreſſing the Strength.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:103365:57"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Signs of a <hi>Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thory?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Antecedent are the Cauſes breeding plenty of Blood, ſuch as are the juſt temper of the Body, Age, the Spring-Seaſon, a temperate Clime, good Diet, and the accuſtomed evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Blood ſuppreſſed. But the conſequent Cauſes are Accidents which demonſtrate an over-fulneſs and predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minancy of the Blood; as, a red colour in the Face, ſwelling of the Veins, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latation of the Veſſels, a ſpontaneous ſtretching Laſſitude, a bigger Bulk of Body, a fleſhy habit of Body, a merry and jocund diſpoſition, ſtupidity, drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs, a ſtrong Pulſe and thick, diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of breathing, and an aptneſs to bleed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is <hi>Cacochymy?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cacochymy</hi> is the redundancy of yellow or black Choler or Flegm; whence it is ſaid to be threefold, Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leric, Melancholic, and Flegmatic.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>By what Signs is a Choleric <hi>Caco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chymy</hi> known?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt, from the Cauſes demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting exuberancy of Choler, as a hot
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:103365:58"/>and dry Conſtitution, a conſtant and florid Age, Summer, a dry Seaſon, a hot and dry Clime, a hot and dry Diet; and then by the ſigns of yellow Choler abounding in the Body, as a pale Face, yellow or blackiſh, a dry Habit of Body, lean, ſlender, hairy, acute Senſes, ſwift and expedite, a ſharp and diligent Wit, little Sleep, and unquiet, much Waking, Dreams of War, a ſwift and frequent Pulſe, want of Stomach, an unquenchable Thirſt, his Vomits and Stools full of Choler, Urine yellow, or ſomewhat inclining to Flame colour, with little ſediment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>By what ſigns is a Melancholy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cochymy underſtood?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt, from the Cauſes ſhewing the Exuberancy of Melancholy; a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Temper, cold and dry, weakneſs of the Spleen, inclining Age, Autumn-Seaſon, ſtrong Diet, a melancholy way of living. Then from the ſeveral ſigns of prevailing Melancholy, a Leaden colour in the Countenance, a dry habit of Body, and lean, a fix'd Aſpect, grim and ſowr, full of fear and ſadneſs,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:103365:58"/>turbulent Sleep, little and ſlow Pulſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>By what Signs is a Flegmatic Cacochymy diſtinguiſh'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt, from the Cauſes that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe Flegm; a Temper cold and moiſt, old Age, Winter-Seaſon, a moiſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Air, unſeaſonable Eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a ſedentary Life, and long Sleep. Then from the Signs demonſtrating redundancy of Flegm; a white livid complexion, ſwell'd cheeks, a large ſat body, ſmall veins, white hair, ſlow in his Actions, thick skull'd, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found ſleeper, dreaming much of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and drowning, a ſlow ſoft Pulſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the containing Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which moſt nearly breeds the Diſeaſe; by ſome call'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd cauſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, I will prove there is no conjoyn'd cauſe. The contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſe is that, which while it is preſent, the Diſeaſe remains; but when it is remov'd, the Diſeaſe ceaſes. But every cauſe of a Diſeaſe being
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:103365:59"/>taken away, the Diſeaſe is not remov'd; therefore there is no containing Cauſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I deny the <hi>Minor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove it; if every cauſe of a Diſeaſe being remov'd, the Diſeaſe ſhould be removd, there would be no need of Remedies to cure a Diſeaſe; but beſide the Remedies which are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to remove the Morbific Cauſe, as for the curing of a bad Temper, which are firſt preſcrib'd for the evacuation of the Humor, cauſing the illneſs of Temper, there are requir'd likewiſe others to correct the bad Temper, as hot Remedies in a cold Diſtemper; therefore the Cauſe being taken away, the Diſeaſe is not remov'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, Where the Cauſe is conjoyn'd with the Diſeaſe, take away the cauſe, and all thoſe diſeaſes are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, nor will there want any further cure. But as to thoſe diſeaſes of which there is no other internal cauſe, but a Plethory or Cacochymy, ſuch as are eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Fevers, tho both thoſe were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd, yet they require proper reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies to perfect the cure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I argue thus; If there were
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:103365:59"/>any conjoyn'd cauſe, it would appear more eſpecially in a <hi>Phlegmone;</hi> for the inherent Humor fix'd in the part in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd, would then be the conjoyn'd cauſe of the <hi>Phlegmone,</hi> but the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and fix'd Hum or into the part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, is not the cauſe conjoyn'd, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no conjoyn'd cauſe of a Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I deny the <hi>Minor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> The Diſeaſe and the Cauſe of the Diſeaſe differ; but that Humor is the <hi>Phlegmone</hi> it ſelf, therefore not the conjoyn'd cauſe of the <hi>Phlegmone.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I deny the <hi>Minor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> Where the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition agrees, to that alſo the thing defin'd agrees; But the Definition of a <hi>Phlegmone</hi> exactly agrees with the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor fix'd in the part inflam'd; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is the <hi>Phlegmone.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I deny the <hi>Minor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>I prove the <hi>Minor.</hi> A <hi>Phlegmone</hi> is a hot diſtemper inflaming the part where it is fix'd, ſwelling and diſtend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, ſo that primarily and of it ſelf it hinders the function of the part;
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:103365:60"/>but that Humor which is infix'd in the part, burns, diſtends, oppreſſes, and ſo being the <hi>Phlegmone,</hi> injures the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction primarily and by it ſelf, without the aggravation of any other Accident.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, That the Humor fix'd in the part inflam'd, is a Subſtance, that the <hi>Phlegmon</hi> is an Accident, therefore differs in the whole <hi>Genus,</hi> ſo far is the Definition from agreeing to both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is the external Cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which happens from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and alters the Body extreamly; call'd the pre-incipient and evident, vulgarly the <hi>Primitive.</hi> And it is ſo much the evident cauſe of the Diſeaſe, by how much it is a thing not natural: For the Air cauſes a Diſeaſe, when it is intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and impure. And the Nouriſhment, if it exceed, or be defective, or if it be bad, or not taken as it ought to be. Alſo Motion and Reſt, Sleep and Waking, when either are immoderate. Alſo when ſuch things are retain'd that ought to be expell'd, and ſuch things are expell'd that ought to be retain'd, they breed a Diſeaſe; as alſo the Paſſions of the Mind, if they be immoderate.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:103365:60"/>
                  <head>Of Symptoms.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Symptom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word <hi>Symptom,</hi> taken in a large ſence, ſignifies whatever happens to a living Creature preternaturally. And ſo it is us'd generally for every preternatural Affection: But properly taken, a Symptom is defin'd, An Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction againſt Nature, which follows the Diſeaſe, as the Shadow follows the Body: And therefore ſome of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian Phyſicians rather choſe to call it the Succedent, then a Symptom, tho the Word Symptom exactly agree with it, as coming from a Greek Word, which ſignifies, to fall together; for no other reaſon, but becauſe it accompanies the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the kinds of Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptoms?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three. Injury of the Actions, Excretion and Retention deviating from the cuſtom of Nature, and ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Affections of the Body preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:103365:61"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the differences of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons injur'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The difference of injur'd Actions is to be gather'd from the number of Actions ſafe and uninjur'd; for they are injuries done either to the Animal, Vital, or Natural Actions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>By how many ways is every one of theſe injur'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Every Animal, Vital and Natural Action is injur'd two ways; either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not done, or ill done: And ill doing is twofold, either feebly, or not as it ought to be. So that there is a threefold annoyance of every Action.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Annoyances of the Animal Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Annoyances of the principal Functions are, the debilitating, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praving and deſtruction of the Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Memory and Ratiocination. Among which, Madneſs, Lunacy and Delirium are accompted chief. The common Injuries of the ſenſible Actions, are, deprivation of the Senſes, and difficulty of Apprehenſion, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes a vitiated Sence. Reſtleſs waking, and drowſie Sleep are accompted Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:103365:61"/>of the inner Senſe; but there are particular injuries of every outward Senſe, as to the Eyes, are, Blindneſs, Dimneſs of Sight, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd Sight; as to the Ears, Deaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Thickneſs of hearing, or a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prav'd Hearing. As to the reſt, tho they want proper terms of expreſſion, yet there is the ſame proportion. Feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its Function has one proper Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptom above all the reſt, which is Pain. The Annoyances of the moving Actions are Immobility, difficult Motion, or a deprav'd Motion, as Trembling, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſive, or Panting. There is alſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Speech, difficulty of Speech, and deprav'd Speech.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Annoyances of the Vital Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Among the Annoyances of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Actions, are reckon'd Privation of the Pulſe, and a deprav'd Pulſe; alſo ſtopping of the Breath, and difficulty of Breathing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Injuries of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Injuries of the Appetite, are, loſs of Stomach, a Canine Appetite, and a deprav'd Appetite.</p>
                     <pb n="110" facs="tcp:103365:62"/>
                     <p>The Injuries of concoction and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, ſlow concoction, and difficult concoction. As many are the Injuries of Retention and Expulſion, tho want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proper Terms. And indeed every Action may be ſaid to be injur'd three wayes; if it be done feebly, or not as it ought to be, or not at all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why does a deprav'd Expulſion and Retention attend the Injuries of the Functions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The due courſe of the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments is impeded, in regard that the expulſive Faculty is exceſſively diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd; and the ſame reaſon for the retentive Faculty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Ametry or Diſorder of the Excrements?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>A vicious annoyance which the Excrements have contracted by rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the due courſe of Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Of how many ſorts is it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Threefold, in Subſtance, in Quantity, and in Quality; in regard that the Purgations of the Body are preternaturally detain'd therein, or elſe recede and deviate from the due courſe of Nature, either in their
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:103365:62"/>whole ſubſtance, or in quantity, or in quality. Thus ſaies <hi>Galen,</hi> Lib. 6. <hi>De Sympt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye call the default of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Excrement is in its whole kind preternatural; as a Stone, Gravel, or Worms: Or elſe, when the manner of Purgation is preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, not the Excrement; as, Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Noſe, Ears, Mouth, Yard, or Belly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the fault of Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the juſt meaſure of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not obſerv'd in Purgation; but that the Excrements come forth either in too great abundance, or too ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Fault of Quality?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the heat of the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments deviates from the cuſtom of Nature, as if they be either black, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid or green; if the ſmell offend more then uſually; if there be any thing of unuſual bitterneſs, ſaltneſs, or acrimony,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:103365:63"/>if any clammineſs, hardneſs or thinneſs more than ordinary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why is the Ametry or Exceſs of Excretion joyn'd with that of Reten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe the Excrements no leſs deviate from the courſe of Nature, nor contract Corruption, when that which ought to come away, is retain'd, then when that which ought to be retain'd, comes away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Symptoms relate to the Irregularity of Retention?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſuppreſſion of the Flowers and Emroids, coſtiveneſs, retention of Sweat and other Excrements, the eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation of which is neceſſary for health.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why d'ye place the preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Affections of the Body which are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to Senſe, next after the Irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of the Excrements?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe they are bred out of the corruption of Excrementitious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many Symptoms are there belonging to the ſenſible Affections of the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are ſaid to be as many as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:103365:63"/>there are Senſes with which they want to be perceived; for ſome are viſible, others audible, others to be ſmelt, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be taſted, others tangible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the viſible preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Affections of the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Unſeemly Colours, which ariſe from the Colours of the ſubject Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors; as, Yellow in the Jaundice, Pale in the Diſeaſe proceeding from Phlegm, call'd <hi>Leucophlegmaſie;</hi> Black, in the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie; then the Shape, Bulk, and all the viſible qualities of the Body chang'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which the Audible Affections?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Preternatural Sounds, as Tink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Ears, Ratling in the Throat and Lungs, Gnaſhing of the Teeth, Belching and breaking Wind; as alſo raving and trembling Speech.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which concern the Smell?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The noyſom Smells which the Arm-pits, Ears, Noſtrils, Mouth, Feet, and the whole Body exhales.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which concern the Taſte.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Bitterneſs in the Mouth ariſing from yellow Choler, Acidneſs from Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy, and Saltneſs from Phlegm.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which belong to the Feeling?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:103365:64"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>All the firſt Qualities, as hot, cold, moiſt and dry, and what derive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from theſe, as, Softneſs, Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Roughneſs, Looſneſs, Rugged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the like, which are perceiv'd in the skin by feeling.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of Signs.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is a Sign?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Whatever being obvious to our Senſes, is attended with ſomething hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, that is a ſign of it. Thus a Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom being conſpicuous, is the expreſs ſign of the latent deſign from whence it flows; in like manner the evident cauſe, as vicious Diet, is the ſign of the Diſeaſe which is occaſion'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts of Signs are there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They reckon up three principal ſorts; wholeſom, which indicate Health; unwholeſom, which indicate a ſickly conſtitution; and neuter, which ſhew a neutral conſtitution between ſick and well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:103365:64"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the ſigns that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate unſoundneſs of Health?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Twofold; Diagnoſtic, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the preſent conſtitution of the Diſeaſe; and Prognoſtic, which por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the future condition of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Some add the <hi>Anamneſtic,</hi> which, by calling to remembrance what was paſt, gueſs at the preſent and future ſtate of the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the Diagnoſtic Signs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Threefold: In regard that ſome demonſtrate the part affected, others the cauſe, others the kind of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; which if proper and inſeparable, are call'd <hi>Pathognomic</hi> Judges of the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; if common and ſeparable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, they are call'd <hi>Aſſociates.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Signs are to be conſider'd for the obtaining the Prognoſtic?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides the proper and inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Symptoms of the Diſeaſe, there are others that come over and above, which declare the bigneſs of the Diſeaſe; and others that appear over and above, which declare the Motion and Nature of the Diſeaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:103365:65"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why are the proper and inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Diagnoſtics of a Diſeaſe numbred among Prognoſticks?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe future conjectures are drawn from the ſpecies of the Diſeaſe; for ſome Diſeaſes in their ſpecies are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable; as in a Cancer: Others cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as a Tertian Fever; ſome ſhort, as Quotidians; others tedious, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctic and Quartans. Add to this, that the proper Symptoms much increaſing, ſignifie the violence of the Diſeaſe, and therefore portend danger; as, if a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement pain in the ſide extend it ſelf to the Throat or Hypochondrium, and there happen a great difficulty of breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and a ſtrong Cough, it is adjudg'd a dangerous Pleuriſie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye call the Symptom <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pervenientia,</hi> or coming over and above?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Symptoms ariſing from the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and increaſe of the Cauſe, which indicate the increaſe of the Diſeaſe; as in a Pleuriſie, Phrenſie, Looſneſs, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of Breath, Redneſs of the Face and Eyes, Spots upon the Breaſt, Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Back and Shoulder-Blades.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What d'ye call Appearing over
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:103365:65"/>and above, or <hi>inſuper apparentia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as beſides the inſeparable Symptomes, manifeſtly ſhew themſelves, as it were going or proceeding forth; ſuch are the ſigns of Crudity or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction, which argue that the Criſis will be ſooner or later.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Criſis?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Criſis is a ſudden change in the Diſeaſe, either to Life or Death: whereby it happens that a Criſis is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good or bad; and both either per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect or imperfect.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What does the Word Criſis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Word <hi>Criſis</hi> comes from a Greek Word that ſignifies to judge, or make a judgment of: So that Criſis is no more then Judgment, and is often taken for the Combat of Nature with the Diſeaſe, and ſometimes for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration and expulſion of noxious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, and ſometimes for the iſſue of the Diſeaſe, be it what it will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which Criſis is perfectly good?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as being ſhewn by the ſigns of Concoction appearing upon the day of the Sign, comes to perfection upon
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:103365:66"/>the Critical day without any dangerous Symptoms, with a manifeſt excretion or purgation according to the <hi>Species</hi> of the Diſeaſe, and Nature of the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is imperfectly good?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which does not altogether remove the Diſeaſe, but cauſes the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient to be more chearful in his Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which Criſis is perfectly bad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which haſtens Death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which is imperfectly evil?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That which precipitates the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient into a worſe condition.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are the Critical Signs divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Some Critical Signs precede, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers accompany, and ſome follow the Criſis.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many Signs precede?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>They are of two ſorts; ſome ſhew the day and time of the Criſis, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers what ſort the future Criſis will be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the ſigns that ſhew the time and day of the Criſis?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſigns of Concoction and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:103365:66"/>which appear in the univerſal Excrements, as Urine and Ordure: For they certainly foretel whether the Criſis will be ſooner or later, and what day Judgment will be made of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe; for if the Urine appear concoct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the fourth day, as, if it have a white ſettlement, ſmooth and equal, it ſhews the Criſis will be upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What more do the ſigns of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and Crudity declare?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>As the ſigns of Crudity ſometimes portend not only diuturnity of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, but Death, ſo the ſigns of Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction promiſe not only a ſhort ſtay of the Diſeaſe, but alſo ſecurity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that perpetual?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes; ſo that the concoction be continual and conſtant; for that is the beſt Urine, ſaies <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> when both the Urine and the Sediment is white, ſmooth and equal, during the whole time, until Judgment be given of the Diſeaſe. But if there be an Intermiſſion, that it be ſometimes pure, and ſometimes crude, with a white, and ſmooth Settlement
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:103365:67"/>now and then, it argues longer conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and leſs ſafety; for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Concoction argues ſtrength of Nature, and predominancy of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Heat. But if the Concoction be interrupted, and that ſigns of Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction appear in the Morning, but none in the Evening, and that the Water be ſometime crude, ſometime concocted, no ſecurity of a Criſis can be expected from ſuch a concoction, for that the Diſeaſe and Nature are upon equal terms, and the Victory remains doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; Nature begins the concoction, but cannot perfect it through Imbecility, or elſe the Malignity of the ſevere Humor, that it will not admit of concoction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Are there no other ſigns that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Time and Day of the Criſis?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides the ſigns of Coction and Crudity, the Motion alſo of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is to be obſerved to tell the time and day of the Criſis. For ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes as move with violence and ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are ſooneſt judged of; thoſe that are extreamly peracute, in the firſt fourth day; peracute, the firſt ſeventh day; ſimply acute, the fourteenth day;
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:103365:67"/>acute, by mutation from ſpecies to ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, may be put off till the fortieth day. The motion alſo of the Diſeaſe declares whether the <hi>Criſis</hi> will happen upon an even or odd day: For when a <hi>Criſis</hi> is only made when Diſeaſes are in their vigor and exaſperation, never in the beginning, nor in the declination, if the exaſperation of the Diſeaſe happen upon an even day, the <hi>Criſis</hi> may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected upon an even day, and ſo on the contrary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the ſigns of a <hi>Criſis</hi> at hand?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſigns that uſually next pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede a <hi>Criſis,</hi> are, a vehement pain in the Head, tumbling and toſſing, anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unquenchable thirſt, an unequal Pulſe, and the like. For as <hi>Hippocrates</hi> ſays, The Night becomes very tedious to them upon whom the <hi>Criſis</hi> is made before the Fit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many ſorts are there of a <hi>Criſis?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two; Excretion, or Removal: For the Tranſlation of every Humor from one part to another, is made ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by flowing forth, or by removal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:103365:68"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the Differences of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleeding at Noſe, Sweating, Looſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Vomit, and Streaming ſorth of the Urine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the ſigns of a <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> by Excretion, or Removal and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Two; for ſome are univerſal, others proper to every ſpecies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Whence are the univerſal gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>From the motion of the Diſeaſe, the part affected, and the Age of the Patient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the motion of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Acute Diſeaſes are judg'd by eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation or excretion; Diuturnal, by removal and ſettlement; for the nature of Acute Diſeaſes conſiſts in quick and vehement, that of Diuturnal Diſeaſes, in a ſlow motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But Diuturnal Diſeaſes are often judg'd by evacuation; ſo <hi>Nicodemus</hi> was judg'd the 24th. day by Urine; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naxion</hi> the 34th by Sweat; and <hi>Cleonae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctides</hi> was perfectly judg'd the 80th. day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:103365:68"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, Chronic Diſeaſes are ſometimes cur'd by excretion, in reſpect of the acute exaſperations that happen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Judgments are to be made from the affected Party.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>If the convex parts of the Liver be inflam'd, a Criſis may be expected either by bleeding at the right Noſtril, or by ſweat, or by ſtream of Urine: but if the hollow parts be affected, the Diſeaſe will be determin'd either by Looſeneſs or by Vomits. Inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Head are judg'd by the Blood burſting forth at the Noſtrils; for there the extremities of the Veſſels end; but Vomiting and Looſeneſs cure the Inflam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of the Meſentery and Stomach.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Conjectures may be made from the Age of the Patient?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleeding at Noſe moſt commonly happens to young men in burning Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; to old men in the ſame Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Looſeneſſes. <hi>Galen</hi> gives this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, becauſe the Humors in young men are full of Choler, thin and ſharp, and therefore flowing upward; in old men Flegmatic, and therefore flowing down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:103365:69"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are the univerſal Signs of a future Criſis; now for the Signs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to every Species. And firſt, what are the ſigns of a critical Bleeding pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently expected?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>If in an acute Feaver you obſerve a redneſs all over the Patients face, a vehement pain in the Head and Neck, a high Pulſe in the Arteries of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, a dimneſs of Sight, and dilatati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Hypochondriums, with diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Breath, you may expect a flux of Blood at the Noſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Give me the reaſon of every ſign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>When the Flux of Blood is near at hand, the Face grows red, the Blood being tranſlated from the lower to the upper parts, and preparing to make its way through the Noſtrils. The pain in the Head and Neck proceeds from the tranſlation of the Morbific Humor, which tearing and rending the membra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous parts, moſt exquiſite in their feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, beget that vehement pain; the Arteries beat high, by reaſon of their compreſſion, which proceeds from the particular repletion of the veins; the Eyes wax dim by reaſon of the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:103365:69"/>of thick Spirits carry'd to the upper parts, that obſtruct the paſſages, not admitting entrance to the Animal Spirits. The Hypochondrium is diſtend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that is, the Liver ſwells, by reaſon of the motion of the Blood, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins its motion at the fountain and roots of the Veins. The difficulty of breathing proceeds from hence, for that the Blood coveting to aſcend, oppreſſes the <hi>Diaphragma,</hi> which is the principal Organ of Reſpiration.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Are there any other Signs of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Bleeding?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Beſides thoſe which are numbred up by <hi>Hippocrates, Galen</hi> adds, Noiſes in the Ears, Tickling in the Noſtrils, ſeeming Apptritions of red things. Thus to a certain young man that lay in an acute Feaver, and ſuddenly leapt out of his Bed, he foretold an inſtant Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for that the young man being by him ask'd why he leapt out of his Bed, when there was nothing to ſcare him? made anſwer, that he ſaw a red Serpent creeping in at the Window.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the betokening ſigns of a critical Sweat?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:103365:70"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Suppreſſion of Urine, and a cold Quivering.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſuppreſſion of Urine?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Becauſe the Matter of Urine and Sweat is the ſame; the ſerous parts of thoſe Humors that are contain'd in the Veins; ſo that there being a Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſerous into the whole Body, the Urine comes to be ſuppreſſed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What cauſes the Shuddering?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Acrimony of the ſerous Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor hurting the Nervous Pannicle, which is of moſt exquiſite ſenſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Are there any other Signs of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Sweat?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Moderns add a ſlow and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Pulſe, fluctuating and uneven, and the fore-running of a hot Vapor ſteam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the Head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the ſigns of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching Looſneſs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Belching, breaking Wind, rumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſwelling of the Belly: For theſe Signs argue the removal of the noxious Humor into the Veins of the Meſentery, and from thence into the Guts. The U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine alſo appears thin and white, the Choleric part being all remov'd into the Belly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:103365:70"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the ſigns of approach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Vomit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are mention'd by <hi>Hippocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes;</hi> a reaching and deſire to Vomit; griping of the Stomach by reaſon of the vicious Humor there harbouring; frequent ſpitting, the Humor evapora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from the Stomach to the Mouth, a darkneſs of ſight, by reaſon of the cloudy Vapour exhaling from the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. Others add a bitterneſs upon the Tongue, and palpitation of the lower Lip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the ſigns of a Flux of Urine?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hippocrates</hi> delivers none; but <hi>Galen</hi> admoniſhes, that they are to be gather'd from the privation of other Purgations. For if no ſigns appear of Bleeding, Sweating, Looſneſs or Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, but that the ſigns of Critical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and Crudity have preceded, it is moſt agreeable to Reaſon that the Diſeaſe muſt be judg'd by Urine, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if there be a heavineſs in the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochondrium, and a burning in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream parts of the Yard, and that the Patient has all along during the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:103365:71"/>made thick and plentiful Water.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>So far for the Signs of Excreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; now tell us the ſigns of a future removal and ſettlement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>In Diuturnal Diſeaſes, where Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not able to throw off the thick Humors by excretion, a Settlement muſt be expected, eſpecially in the Winter; alſo if Purgation were by Nature begun, but not perfected; or if the Patient have made thin and crude Urine during the whole courſe of the Diſeaſe, with healthful and good ſigns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell us now the Signs portending a good or bad Criſis?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether the Criſis be good or bad, we judge by the Signs concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and ſubſequent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which d'ye call Signs concomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as appear with the Criſis it ſelf, ſo that the Excretion or Settlement happening, eaſily ſhew whether it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e good or bad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the ſigns of a good Excretion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>To make an Excretion advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous, four things are requir'd, conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:103365:71"/>Quality, ſufficient Quantity, ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Time, and a manner of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion familiar to Nature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What Quality is requir'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That quality is moſt to be commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed when the peccant Humor is purg'd out after due concoction; for the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and Expulſion of crude Humors is bad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is Quantity?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>It ought to be moderate: For as immoderate Expulſion is dangerous, in regard all Exceſs is an Enemy to Nature, ſo of critical. Excrements there ought to be no ſmall purgation; for a ſmall Expulſion ſhews that the more copious and malignant Humors cannot be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by Nature; or elſe it ſhews la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Nature's ſudden Diſſolution: And therefore little Sweats, Droppings of Blood, and Vomits in ſmall Quantity are all condemn'd by <hi>Hippocrates;</hi> for all the noxious Humor, not any part of it ought to be evacuated; in regard that what is left after the Criſis in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, is the occaſion of a Relapſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What time?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon the critical day; for all
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:103365:72"/>other expulſions are to be ſuſpected.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Method of Purgation?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Purgation ought to come forth all together in a good quantity, and not by degrees, through the places proper, not through the nobler parts; not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely, but in a ſtreight line through the open paſſages.</p>
                     <p>Thus when the Spleen is affected, for the Blood to burſt from the right No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtril; and when the Liver is affected, to break out at the left Noſtril, is evil. For excretion in a ſtraight line argues a ſtronger contention of Nature; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as oblique excretion argues the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Humor, the weakneſs of the Part oppreſſed, and an obſtruction of the Paſſages.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the good conditions of a wholeſom Abſceſs or Settlement of the bad Humor?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>In a wholeſom <hi>Abſceſs</hi> three things are requiſite in the Opinion of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates; Where, from whence,</hi> and <hi>for what reaſon. Where,</hi> denotes the Part where the ſettlement is made, which ought to be ſome inferiour or more ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble Part, remote from the Part affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:103365:72"/>capable to contain all the Morbific Matter, otherwiſe there is danger of a reflux. <hi>From whence,</hi> denotes from what Part the Matter is remov'd, from the right or the left; for the removal ought to be in a ſtraight line. <hi>For what reaſon,</hi> denotes the cauſe of the removal; that is, whether through a true concoction of the morbific matter, or whether by ſome unſeaſonable provocation; for if it happen while the matter of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is crude, the conſequence will be evil.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>There remain the conſequent ſigns, that ſhew us either a proſperous or doubtful <hi>Criſis.</hi> From whence are they gather'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>From the Quality of the Body, the Actions and Excrements.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is to be regarded in the Quality of the Body?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The Quality of the Body is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd by the colour and bulk. If the Face be well colour'd, the excretion or purgation was wholeſom; if the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour be livid, yellowiſh, or black, the purgation is ſymptomatical; if the ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Face falls, that was ſwell'd
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:103365:73"/>before, the <hi>Criſis</hi> is perfect; if it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue puffie, there is ſome fear of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What as to the Actions?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Whether the Actions Natural, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and Animal are right: If there be a good Reception, Concoction and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, the <hi>Criſis</hi> is true and good; if kecking, loathing of Meat, ſowr Belches, and offenſive to the ſmell, Thirſt and Extenſion of the Hypochondriums, a Relapſe is to be fear'd; if an equal and more remiſs Pulſe, eaſie reſpiration, and temperate heat, the <hi>Criſis</hi> is ſafe; if a thick Pulſe, and an ardent heat, it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues a remaining want of Temper in ſome of the Bowels, which may breed a new generation of Humor; if the Mind and Senſes be at eaſe and ſound; if the Patient ſleep quietly, and turn without diſturbance from one ſide to the other, it argues a good <hi>Criſis;</hi> the contrary juſtifies an evil one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What as to the Excrements?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>If the Excrements be well colour'd and figur'd, and the Urine like thoſe of healthy people, they teſtifie a healthy <hi>Criſis;</hi> if thin or red, they threaten a relapſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:103365:73"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell me now the difference of Critical Days?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>There are three differences of Critical Days; ſome are truly Critical, call'd principal; others Indicatory, and others ſuch as fall between the Principal and the Indicatory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What are the Days truly Critical?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Such as judge perfectly, faithfully, manifeſtly, and without danger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are the principal Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Days?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three; the ſeventh, fourteenth, and twentieth. The ſeventh is the term of peracute Diſeaſes; the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth, of ſimply acute; the twentieth of acute Diſeaſes, that were ſlow from the beginning, or ſuch whoſe Acuteneſs did not laſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Cauſe of Critical Days.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The cauſe of Critical Days is twofold; the one Material, the other Efficient. The Material is a noxious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor, peccant both in quality and quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity. The Efficient is twofold; the one univerſal, and moſt remote; the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, all whoſe Influences the inferior
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:103365:74"/>Moon receives, and communicates them to us. The other particular and near, that is to ſay, Nature; which tho void of Counſel and Reaſon, has certain mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions confin'd to certain Order, and therefore has made choice of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, fourteenth, and twentieth day, for the Perfection of <hi>Criſis</hi>'s.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>But why is the twentieth day more critical then the twenty firſt, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Sevenths are perfectly criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>I anſwer, that the twenty firſt is the end of the third Seventh; for of the three Sevenths only the firſt is to be reckon'd whole, and the ſecond is copu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated with the third, ſo that the four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day is the beginning of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and beginning of the third.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Why are both the latter Sevenths coupled together ſhorter by one day then the firſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>That happens for two reaſons: the firſt is, becauſe the natural Motion, of which kind is the Critical, is ſlower in the beginning, ſwifter in the end: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, becauſe the morbifick Matter attenuated and mitigated during the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:103365:74"/>firſt Seventh, is more eaſily and ſwiftly expell'd by Nature in the following Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Is not the 21ſt. ſometimes critical?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes; for in regard the thicker and more contumacious Matter of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is not ſo eaſily overcome by Nature, the <hi>Criſis</hi> is ſometimes prolong'd to the 21th. day, and then the Septenaries are all equal: Therefore, ſays <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> when a <hi>Criſis</hi> happens upon odd days, there is the 3, 7, 9, 11, 14, 17, 21. Sweats are good in Feavers that appear upon the 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 14, 17, 21; ſo that altho we give the pre-eminence to the 20, yet we do not exclude the 21th.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the indicatory days?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe which prepare us to judge the future Criſis upon the three ſeventh days.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How many are they reckon'd to be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Three; the 4th. 11th. 17th. To which the Prerogative of judging is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd; for the Judgment made upon thoſe days is imperfect; only they may give ſome light into the true Criſis; for the 4th. is the Index of the 7th. the 10th. of the 14th. and the 17th. of the 20th.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:103365:75"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that perpetual?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes; if there be nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal or external that diſturbs the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary courſe of Nature; as if the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian has not miſtaken, or that the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient or Tenders have not gone accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Directions: For it may happen through ſome external cauſe, that the 4th. may not always be the Index of the 7th. nor the 11th. of the 14. nor the 17th. of the 21th.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>Which are the interfalling days?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe that provoke Nature, and cauſe Purgations before their time, as in the firſt Septenary the third and fifth, in the ſecond, the 9th. and 13th. in the third, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he 19th. Theſe days are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catory and preparatory, becauſe they are uneven; but the Criſis that is made upon thoſe days is imperfect and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, in regard that Nature is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked by the malignant Quality of the morbific Humor, that ſhe only expels crude and concocted together, and good Humors with bad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D.</speaker>
                     <p>How are the other Days call'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>C.</speaker>
                     <p>The other interfalling days, are, the 6th. 8th. 10th. 12th. 16th. 18th. and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:103365:75"/>theſe are call'd Vacant Days, becauſe they are neither Critical, nor Indica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, nor Provocative. For tho ſome Purgations may happen upon thoſe days, yet they all proceed from the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignity of the Diſeaſe, not from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture either victorious or exaſperated, and therefore they are only Symptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, not Critical.</p>
                     <p>The 6th. of all dayes is the worſt, cruel, treacherous, and altogether an Enemy to the 7th. Wherefore the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is lik'nd to a merciful Prince, who reſcues many from Deſtruction; the 6th. day by <hi>Galen</hi> is call'd a Tyrant, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it precipitates all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e ſick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Tombs, or at leaſt to great danger of Death.</p>
                     <p>The Vacant Days by ſome Learned Phyſitians are call'd Med'cinal, becauſe upon thoſe Days the Phyſician may ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſter his Cathartic Remedies, which he dares not do upon the Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal days, for fear of diſturbing Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103365:76"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>Dorman Newman</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Compleat Treatie of the Muſcles, as they appear in Humane Bodies, and ariſe in Diſſection: with diverſe Anatomical Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions not yet diſcovered. Illuſtrated with near 40 Copper Plates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>J. Brown,</hi> Sworn Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon in ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Valentine</hi> his Triumphant Chariot of Antimony, with Annotations of <hi>Theodore Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ingius,</hi> M. D. With the True Book of the Learned <hi>Syneſius,</hi> concerning the Philoſophers Stone, in 80.—With Cuts.</p>
            <p>Exercitationes Anatomicae a <hi>Roberto Bayfield.</hi> Editio ſecunda. 12.</p>
            <p>Philoſophical Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>logues concerning the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Natural I Bodies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>W. Simpſon,</hi> M. D. in 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Medela Medicorum;</hi> or, An Enquiry into the Reaſons and Grounds of the Contempt of Phyſicians and their Noble Art: By Dr. <hi>Simpſon.</hi> in 12.</p>
            <p>An Eſſay towards the Hiſtory and Cure of Feavers. By Dr. <hi>Simpſon:</hi> in 12.</p>
            <p>The Method and Means of enjoying Health and Long Life; Adapting peculiar Courſes for different Conſtitutions, Ages, Abilities; Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinary States, Individual Proprieties, Habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated Cuſtoms, and paſſions of Mind: Suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Preſervatives and Correctives to every Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for attainment thereof. By <hi>Edward M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waring,</hi> M. D. 80.</p>
            <p>Kitchen-Phyſick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 80.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
